<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Triplici nodo, triplex cuneus. Or An apologie for the Oath of allegiance against the two breues of Pope Paulus Quintus, and the late letter of Cardinal Bellarmine to G. Blackvvel the Arch-priest. Authoritate regiâ.</title>
            <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856489</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22043</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04285)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22043)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 740:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Triplici nodo, triplex cuneus. Or An apologie for the Oath of allegiance against the two breues of Pope Paulus Quintus, and the late letter of Cardinal Bellarmine to G. Blackvvel the Arch-priest. Authoritate regiâ.</title>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
                  <author>Paul V, Pope, 1552-1621.</author>
                  <author>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, Saint, 1542-1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By James I. Royal arms on title page verso.</note>
                  <note>Includes translations of the breves and of the letter.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" in a mortised ornament.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An apologie for the oath of allegiance.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paul --  V, --  Pope, 1552-1621 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, --  Saint, 1542-1621 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22043:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22043:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Triplici nodo, triplex cuneus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR AN APOLOGIE FOR THE OATH of Allegiance, <hi>Againſt the two</hi> Breues <hi>of Pope</hi> PAVLVS QVINTVS, and the late Letter of Cardinal BELLAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINE to G. BLACKVVEL the Arch-prieſt.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tunc omnes populi clamauerunt &amp; dixerunt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Magna eſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritas, &amp; praeualet.</hi>
               </l>
               <bibl>ESDR. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Authoritate Regiâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Barker,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>ANNO 1607.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="justification">
            <pb facs="tcp:22043:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22043:2"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGIE FOR THE OATH of Allegiance.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat a monſtrous, rare, nay neuer heard of treacherous attempt, was plotted within theſe few yeeres here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, for the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Maieſtie, the Queene, their Poſteritie, the whole houſe of Parliament, and a great number of good Subiects of all ſorts, and degrees, is ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous already through the whole World by the infamy thereof, as it is needleſſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated or publiſhed any more, the horror of the ſinne it ſelfe doth ſo lowdly proclaime it. For if thoſe <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 4 10.</note> crying ſinnes, (whereof men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22043:3"/>
is made in the Scripture) haue that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithet giuen them for their publique infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and for procuring as it were with a lowd cry from Heauen, a iuſt vengeance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence; and yet thoſe ſinnes are both old and too common, neither the world nor any one Countrey being euer at any time cleane voyd of them: If thoſe Sinnes, I ſay, are ſaid in the Scripture to cry ſo lowd; What muſt then this Sinne doe, plotted without cauſe, infinite in crueltie, and ſingular from all examples? What proceeded hereupon, is likewiſe notorious to the whole world, His Maieſties Iuſtice onely taking holde vpon the Offenders, and that in as Honourable and publique a forme of triall, as euer was vſed in this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>2. For although the onely reaſon they gaue for plotting ſo heinous an attempt, was the zeale they caried to the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; yet were neuer any other of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion the worſe vſed for that cauſe, as by his Maieſties gratious Proclamation imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after the diſcouery of the ſaid Fact doeth plainely appeare; Onely at the next
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22043:3"/>
ſitting downe againe of the Parliament, were there Lawes made, ſetting downe ſome ſuch orders as was thought fit for preuenting the like miſchiefe in time to come. Amongſt which, a forme of Oath was framed to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by all his Maieſties Subiects, whereby they ſhould make cleare profeſsion of their Reſolution, faithfully to perſiſt in his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties obedience according to their naturall Allegiance; To the end that hereby his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie might make a ſeparation, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene all his good Subiects in generall, and vnfaithfull Traitors, that intended to with draw themſelues from his Maieſties Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; But ſpecially to make a ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſo many of his Maieſties Subiects, who although they were otherwiſe Popiſhly affected, yet retained in their hearts the print of their naturall duetie to their Soueraigne; and thoſe who being caried away with the like Fanaticall zeale that the Powder Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors were, could not conteine themſelues within the bounds of their naturall Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but thought diuerſitie of Religion a ſafe pretext for all kinde of Treaſons, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22043:4"/>
againſt their Soueraigne. Which godly and wiſe intent God did bleſſe with ſucceſſe accordingly: For very many of his Maieſties Subiects that were Popiſhly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, aſwell Prieſts, as Layicks, did freely take the ſame Oath: whereby they both gaue his Maieſtie occaſion to thinke the better of their fidelitie, and likewiſe freed themſelues of that heauy ſlander, That although they were fellow profeſſors of one Religion with the powder Traitors, yet were they not ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them in Treaſonable courſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Soueraigne; whereby all quietly minded Papiſts were put out of deſpaire, and his Maieſtie gaue good proofe that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no perſecution againſt them for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cauſe, but onely deſired to be ſecured of them for Ciuill obedience, which for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cauſe they were bound to performe.</p>
            <p>3. But the deuil could not haue deuiſed a more malitious tricke for interrupting this ſo calme and clement a courſe, then fell out by the ſending hither, and publiſhing a <hi>Breue</hi> of the Popes, countermaunding all them of his profeſsion to take this Oath;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22043:4"/>
Thereby ſowing new ſeedes of iealouſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his Maieſtie and his Popiſh Subiects, by ſtirring them vp to diſobey that lawfull commandement of their Soueraigne, which was ordeined to be taken of them as a pledge of their fidelitie; And ſo by their refuſall of ſo iuſt a charge, to giue his Maieſtie ſo great and iuſt a ground for puniſhment of them, without touching any matter of Conſcience, throwing them needleſly into one of theſe deſperate ſtraights, Either with the loſſe of their liues and goods, to renounce their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to their natural Soueraigne; Or elſe to procure the condemnation of their ſoules, by renouncing the Catholicke faith, as he alleadgeth.</p>
            <p>4. And on the other part, although di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparitie of Religion can permit no intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, nor intercourſe of Meſſengers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his Maieſtie and the Pope; yet there being no denounced warre betweene them, he hath by this Action broken the rules of common ciuilitie, and Iuſtice betweene Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes, in thus condemning him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, both by accounting him a Perſecutor,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22043:5"/>
which cannot be but implyed by exhorting the Papiſts to endure Martyrdome; As like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by ſo ſtraightly commanding all thoſe of his profeſsion in England, to refuſe the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Oath, Thereby refuſing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their naturall obedience to their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne. For if he thinke himſelfe his Maieſties Iudge, wherefore hath he condemned him vnheard? And, if he haue nothing to doe with the King and his gouernment, (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he hath not) why doeth he <hi>mittere fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem in alienam meſſem?</hi> to meddle betweene his Maieſtie and his Subiects, eſpecially in matters that meerely and onely concerne Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil obedience? And yet could <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> in his greateſt furie, and auowed quarrel againſt the late Queene, doe no more iniury vnto her, then he hath in this caſe offered vnto his Maieſtie, without ſo much as a pretended or an alleadged cauſe. For what difference there is, betweene the commanding Subiects to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, and looſing them from their oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance as <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> did, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding of Subiects not to obey in making profeſsion of their Oath of their duetifull
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22043:5"/>
Allegiance, as this Pope hath now done; No man can eaſily diſcerne.</p>
            <p>5. But to draw neere vnto his <hi>Breue.</hi> Wherein certainly he hath taken more pains then he needed, by ſetting downe in the ſaid <hi>Breue</hi> the whole body of the Oath at length, whereas the onely naming of the Title there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of might as well haue ſerued for any anſwere he hath made thereunto, making <hi>Vna litura,</hi> that is, the flat and generall condemnation of the whole Oath, to ferue for all his refuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherein he hath as well in this reſpect as in the former, dealt both vndiſcreetly with his Maieſtie, and iniuriouſly with his owne Catholicks. With his Maieſtie, in not refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting particularly what ſpecial words he quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled in that Oath; which if he had done, it might haue bene that his Maieſtie for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care he hath, not to put any of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to a needleſſe extremitie, might haue bene contented in ſome ſort to haue refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or interpreted thoſe wordes: With his owne Catholikes, Either if his Maieſtie had ſo done, they had bene thereby fully eaſed in that buſineſſe; Or at leaſt, if his Maieſtie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22043:6"/>
would not haue condeſcended to haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered any thing in the ſaid Oath, yet would thereby ſome appearance or ſhadow of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe haue bene left vnto them for refuſing the ſame, not as ſeeming thereby to ſwarue from their Obedience and Allegiance vnto his Maieſtie, but onely being ſtayed from taking the ſame vpon the ſcrupulous tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their Conſciences, in regard of thoſe particular words which the Pope had noted and condemned therein.</p>
            <p>And now let vs heare the wordes of his Thunder.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="popes_letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:22043:6"/>
            <head>POPE PAVLVS the fifth, to the Engliſh Catholikes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Elbeloued ſonnes, Salutation <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Pope his firſt</hi> Breue.</note> and Apostolicall Benediction. The tribulations and calamities, which ye haue continually ſusteined for the keeping of the Catholike Faith, haue alwayes afflicted vs with great griefe of minde: But for as much as we vnderstand, that at this time all things are more grieuous, our affliction hereby is wonderfully increaſed. For we haue heard how you are compelled by most grieuous puniſhments ſet before you, to goe to the Churches of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, to frequent their Aſſemblies, to be preſent at their Sermons. Truely wee doe vndoubtedly beleeue, that they which with ſo great constancie and fortitude, haue hither to indured almost infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and most cruel perſecutions, that they may walke without ſpot in the Law of the Lord, will neuer ſuffer themſelues to bee defiled with the communion of thoſe that haue forſaken the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Law. Yet notwithstanding, being compelled
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22043:7"/>
by the zeale of our Pastorall Office, and by our Fatherly care which we doe continually take for the ſaluation of your ſoules, we are inforced to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh, and deſire you, that by no meanes you come vnto the Churches of the Heretikes, or heare their Sermons, or communicate with them in their Rites, lest you incurre the wrath of God. For theſe things may yee not doe without inda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maging the worſhip of God, and your owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As likewiſe you cannot without most eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and grieuous wronging of Gods Honour, binde your ſelues by the Oath, which in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we haue heard with very great griefe of our heart is administred vnto you, of the tenor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der written. viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I A. B. doe truely and ſincerely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <note place="margin">The Oath.</note> profeſſe, teſtifie, and declare in my conſcience before God and the world, That our Soueraigne Lord King IAMES, is lawfull King of this Realme, and of all other his Maieſties Dominions and Countreys; And that the Pope neither of himſelfe, nor by any authoritie of the Church or Sea of</hi> Rome, <hi>or by any other meanes with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath any power or authoritie to depoſe</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:22043:7"/>
               <hi>the King, or to diſpoſe any of his Maieſties Kingdomes, or Dominions, or to authorize any forraigne Prince, to inuade or annoy him, or his Countreys, or to diſcharge any of his Subiects of their Allegiance, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his Maieſtie, or to giue Licence or leaue to any of them to beare Armes, raiſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, or to offer any violence, or hurt to his Maieſties Royall perſon, State or Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to any of his Maieſties Subiects within his Maieſties Dominions. Alſo I doe ſweare from my heart, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any declaration or ſentence of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, or depriuation made or gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or to be made or granted, by the Pope or his ſucceſſors, or by any Authoritie deriued, or pretended to be deriued from him, or his Sea, againſt the ſaid King, his Heires, or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, or any Abſolution of the ſaid ſubiects from their Obedience, I wil beare faith and true Allegiance to his Maieſtie, his Heires and Succeſſors, and him and them will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend to the vttermoſt of my power, againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſoeuer, which ſhal be made againſt his or their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:22043:8"/>
               <hi>their Crowne and dignitie, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence, or declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or otherwiſe, and will doe my beſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to diſcloſe and make knowen vnto his Maieſtie, his Heires and Succeſſors, all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and traiterous Conſpiracies, which I ſhall know or heare of, to be againſt him or any of them. And I doe further ſweare, That I doe from my heart abhorre, deteſt and abiure, as impious and Hereticall, this damnable doctrine and Poſition, That Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which be Excommunicated or depriued by the Pope, may be depoſed, or murthered by their Subiects, or any other whatſoeuer. And I doe beleeue, and in conſcience am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, that neither the Pope, nor any perſon whatſoeuer, hath power to abſolue me of this Oath, or any part thereof, which I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge by good and full Authoritie to be lawfully miniſtred vnto me, and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all pardons and diſpenſations to the contrary. And all theſe things I doe plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerely acknowledge and ſweare, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe expreſſe wordes by me ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and according to the plaine and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:22043:8"/>
               <hi>ſenſe and vnderſtanding of the ſame words, without any Aequiuocation, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall euaſion, or ſecret reſeruation whatſoeuer. And I doe make this Recognition and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement heartily, willingly and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vpon the true Faith of a Chriſtian. So helpe me GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which things ſince they are thus; it muſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare vnto you by the words themſelues, That ſuch an Oath cannot be taken without hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Catholique Faith, and the Saluation of your Soules, ſeeing it conteines many things, which are flat contrary to Faith and Saluation. Wherefore wee doe admoniſh you, that you doe vtterly abſtaine from taking this and the like Oathes: which thing we doe the more earneſtly require of you becauſe we haue experience of the Conſtancie of your Faith, which is tried like Gold in the fire of perpetuall Tribulation. We doe well knowe, that you will cheerefully vnder-goe all kinde of cruell Torments whatſoeuer, yea, and conſtantly endure death it ſelfe, rather then you wil any thing offend the Maieſtie of <hi>God.</hi> And this our Confidence is confirmed by thoſe things, which are dayly reported vnto vs, of the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22043:9"/>
vertue, valour and fortitude, which in theſe last times, doeth no leſse ſhine in your <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> then it did in the firſt beginnings of the Church. Stand therefore, your Loynes being girt about with Veritie, and hauing on the Breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of Righteouſneſſe, taking the Shielde of Faith, be ye ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might; And let nothing hinder you. He which will crowne you, and doeth in Heauen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde your Conflicts, will finiſh the good worke, which he hath begun in you. You knowe how he hath promiſed his Diſciples, that hee will neuer leaue them Orphanes: for hee is faithfull which hath promiſed. Hold faſt therefore his correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is, being rooted and grounded in Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Whatſoeuer ye doe, whatſoeuer ye indeuour, doe it with one accord, in ſimplicity of Heart, in meekeneſſe of Spirit, without murmuring or doubting. For by this doe all men knowe, that we are the Diſciples of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> if we haue Loue one to another. Which Charitie, as it is very greatly to be deſired of all faithfull Chriſtians: So certainely is it altogether neceſſarie for you, moſt bleſsed Sonnes. For by this your Charitie, the Power of the Deuill is weakened, who doeth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22043:9"/>
ſo much aſſaile you, ſince that Power of his is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially vpheld by the Contentions, and Diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of our Sonnes. We exhort you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Bowels of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> by whoſe Loue we are taken out of the Iawes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Death; That aboue all things, you would haue mutuall Charitie among you. Surely Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eight of happy memorie, hath giuen you moſt profitable Precepts of practiſing bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Charitie one to another, in his Letters, in forme of a <hi>Breue,</hi> to our welbeloued Sonne M. <hi>George</hi> Arch priest of the Kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, dated the 5. day of the moneth of October, 1602. Put them therefore diligently in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and bee not hindered by any difficultie or doubtfulneſse. We require you, that ye doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly obſerue the words of thoſe Letters, and that yee take and vnderſtand them ſimply as they ſound, and as they lie, all Power to interpret them otherwiſe, being taken away. In the meane while, we will neuer ceaſe to pray to the Father of Mercies, that hee would with pitie beholde your afflictions, and your paines, And that hee would keepe and defend you with his continuall Protection: whome wee doe gently greete with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22043:10"/>
our Apoſtolicall Benediction. Dated at <hi>Rome</hi> at S. <hi>Marke,</hi> vnder the Signet of the Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the tenth of the Calends of October, 1606. the ſecond yeere of our <hi>Pope-dome.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <head>THE ANSWERE TO the firſt <hi>Breue.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt the Pope expreſſeth herein his Sorrow for that Perſecution, which the Catholiques ſuſtaine for the faiths ſake. Wherein, beſides the maine vntrueth, whereby the King our Maſter is ſo iniuriouſly vſed, I muſt euer auowe and maintaine, as the trueth is, according to mine owne knowledge, that Her Maieſtie neuer puniſhed any Papiſt for Religion, but that their owne puniſhment was euer extorted out of her hands againſt her will, by their owne misbehauiour, which both the time and circumſtances of her
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22043:10"/>
Actions will manifeſtly make proofe of. For before <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> his Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on giuing her ouer for a Pray, and ſetting her Subiects at libertie to rebell, It is wel knowen ſhee neuer medled with the blood or hard puniſhment of any Catholique, nor made any rigorous Lawes againſt them. And ſince that Time, who liſt to compare with an indifferent eye, the manifold intended Inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions againſt her whole Kingdome, The forraine Practiſes, The internall publike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, The priuate Plots and Machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, poyſonings, murthers, and all ſorts of deuiſes, <hi>Et quid non?</hi> dayly ſet abroach; and all theſe Wares continually foſtered and fomented from <hi>Rome;</hi> Together with the continuall corrupting of her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, as well by temporall Bribes, as by faire and ſpecious promiſes of eternall felicitie; And nothing but booke vpon booke pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely ſet foorth by all her Fugitiues, for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of ſo Holy deſignes: Who liſt, I ſay, with an indifferent eye, to looke on the one part, vpon thoſe infinite and intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Temptations, And on the other part vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22043:11"/>
the iuſt, yet moderate puniſhment of a part of theſe hainous Offenders; ſhall eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee that gracious Prince as free from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, as they ſhall free theſe helliſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments from the Honor of Martyrdome.</p>
            <p>5. But now hauing ſacrificed (if I may ſo ſay) to the <hi>Manes</hi> of my defunct Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, as well for the diſcharge of my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular duetie, as for loue of Veritie; I muſt next performe my duetie to his Maieſtie preſent, in teſtifying likewiſe the truth of his Actions in this matter. Wherein I muſt for the loue of Veritie confeſſe, That whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was her iuſt and mercifull Gouernement ouer the Papiſts in her Time, his Maieſties Gouernement ouer them ſince hath ſo farre exceeded hers, in Mercie and Clemencie, as not onely the Papiſts themſelues grewe to that height of Pride, in confidence of his mildeneſſe, as they did directly expect, and aſſuredly promiſe to themſelues libertie of Conſcience &amp; Equalitie with vs in all things; But euen we, I muſt truely confeſſe, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties beſt and faithfulleſt Subiects, were caſt in great feare and amazement of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22043:11"/>
Courſe and proceedings, Euer progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticating and iuſtly ſuſpecting that ſowre fruite to come of it, which ſhewed it ſelfe clearely in the powder-Treaſon. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did his Maieſtie honour with Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, <note place="margin">His Maieſties Benefits and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours beſtowed vpon the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques.</note> of knowen and open Recuſants? How indifferently did his Maieſtie giue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and acceſſe to both ſides, beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally all Fauours and Honors on both Profeſsions? How free and continuall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, had all Rankes and Degrees of Papiſts in his Court and Companie? And aboue all, how frankely and freely did his Maieſtie free Recuſants of their ordinarie payments? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is euident what ſtraite order was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out of his Maieſties owne mouth to his Iudges, to ſpare the Execution of all Prieſts, (notwithſtanding their Conuiction,) Ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereunto a Gracious Proclamation, whereby all Prieſts, that were at libertie, and not taken, might goe out of the Countrey by ſuch a day: his Maieſties Generall Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don hauing bene extended to all conuicted Prieſts in priſon, whereupon they were ſet at libertie as good Subiects, And all Prieſtes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22043:12"/>
that were taken after, ſent ouer and ſet at Libertie there. But time and paper wil raile me to make enumeration of all the Benefits and Gracious fauours that his Maieſtie hath beſtowed in generall and particular vpon Papiſts: In recounting wherof, euery ſcrape of my penne would ſerue but for a blot of the Popes ingratitude and Iniuſtice, in meating him with ſo hard a meaſure for the ſame. So as I thinke I haue ſufficiently, or at leaſt with good reaſon wiped the <note n="a" place="margin">Magno cum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi moerore. &amp;c.</note> Teares from the Popes eyes, for complaining vpon ſuch perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, who if he had bin but politikely wiſe, although hee had had no reſpect to Iuſtice and Veritie, would haue in this Complaint of his, made a difference betweene the times of the late Queene, and his Maieſtie nowe preſent; And in his commending of our So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueraignes Moderation, in regard of former times, might haue had hope to haue moued his Maieſtie to haue continued in the ſame clement courſe. For it is a true ſaying, That alledged kindneſſe vpon noble mindes doeth euer worke much. And for the maine vntrueth of his Maieſties perſecution, it can
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22043:12"/>
neuer be proued, that any were, or are put to death in his Maieſties time for cauſe of Conſcience, except that now this diſcharge giuen by the Pope to all Catholiques to take their Oath of Allegiance to his Maieſtie be the cauſe of the due puniſhment of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: which if it fall out to be, let the blood light vpon the Popes head, who is the onely cauſe thereof.</p>
            <p>As for the next poynt conteined in his <hi>Breue</hi> concerning his diſcharge of all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to come to our Church, or frequent our Rites and Ceremonies, I am not to meddle <note place="margin">The intende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Diſcourſe.</note> at this time with that matter, becauſe my Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand now onely is to publiſh to the World the Iniurie and Iniuſtice done vnto his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie in diſcharging his owne Subiects to make profeſsion of their Obedience to him. Now as to the poynt wherein the Oath is quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, it is ſet downe in fewe, but very weightie words; To wit, that it ought to be cleare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Catholiques, <hi>That this Oath cannot be taken with ſafetie of the Catholike Faith, and of their Soules health, ſince it conteineth many things that are plainely and directly contrary to</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:22043:13"/>
               <hi>their faith &amp; ſaluation.</hi> To this, the old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fathered vpon the Philoſopher may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fitly be applied, <hi>Multa dicit, ſed pauca pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat:</hi> Nay indeed, <hi>Nihil omnino probat.</hi> For how the profeſsion of the naturall Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Subiects to their Prince, can be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to the faith and ſaluation of ſoules, is ſo farre beyond my ſimple reading in Diuinitie, as I muſt thinke it a ſtrange and new Aſſertion, to proceede out of the mouth of that pretended generall Paſtor of all Chriſtian ſoules. I reade in deede, and not in one, or two, or three places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that Subiects are bound to obey their Princes for conſcience ſake, whether they were good or wicked Princes. So ſaid the people to <note n="a" place="margin">Ioſh. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſhua, As we obeyed</hi> Moyſes <hi>in all things, ſo wil we obey thee.</hi> So the <note n="b" place="margin">Iere. 27. 12.</note> Prophet commanded the people to obey the King of Babel, ſaying, <hi>Put your neckes vnder the yoke of the King of Babel, and ſerue him and his people, that yee may liue.</hi> So were the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael vnto <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 5. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> deſiring him to let them goe. So to <note n="d" place="margin">Ezra. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Cyrus,</hi> obtaining leaue of him to returne to build the Temple. And
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22043:13"/>
in a word, the <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 13. 5.</note> Apoſtle willed all men <hi>to be ſubiect for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Agreeably to the Scriptures did the Fathers teach. <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>August in Pſal.</hi> 124.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Iulian,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Iulian was an vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing Emperour, was hee not an Apoſtata, an Oppreſſour, and an Idolater? Chriſtian Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſerued that vnbeleeuing Emperour: when they came to the cauſe of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>they would acknowledge no Lord, but him that is in Heauen. When he would haue them to worſhip Idoles and to ſacrifice, they preferred</hi> GOD <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: But when he ſaid, Goe foorth to fight, Inuade ſuch a nation, they preſently obeyed. They diſtinguiſhed their Eternal Lord from their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and yet were they ſubiect euen vnto their temporall lord for his ſake that was their eternall Lord and Maſter.</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Tertul. ad Scap.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, <hi>A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is enemy to no man, much leſſe to the Prince, whom he knoweth to be appointed of God, &amp; ſo of neceſsity must loue, reuerence &amp; honour him, and wiſh him ſafe with the whole Romane Empire, ſo long as the world ſhall last: for ſo long ſhall it endure. Wee honour therefore the Emperour in ſuch ſort, as is lawfull for vs, and expedient for him, as a man, the next vnto God, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:22043:14"/>
               <hi>from God whatſoeuer he hath, and onely inferiour vnto God. This the Emperour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would: for ſo is be greater then all, while he is inferiour onely to the true God.</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iust Martyr Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Ant. Imperat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iustine Martyr; We onely adore God, and in all other things cheerefully performe ſeruice to you, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsing that you are Emperours and Princes of men.</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Amb. in orat. con. Auxentium de baſilicis tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. habetur. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Epist. Amb.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe; I may lament, weepe, and ſigh: My teares are my weapons againſt their Armes, Souldiers, and the</hi> Gothes <hi>alſo, ſuch are the weapons of a Prieſt: Otherwiſe neither ought I, neither can I reſist.</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Optat. contra Parme. lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Optatus; Ouer the Emperour, there is none but only God, that made the Emperour. And</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. Mag. Epiſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>indict.</hi> 11. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 61.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> writing to <hi>Mauritius</hi> about a certaine Law, that a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier ſhould not be receiued into a Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>Nondum expleta militia; The Almightie God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>holdes him guiltie, that is not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to the moſt excellent Emperours in all things that hee doeth or ſpeaketh.</hi> And then calling himſelfe the vnworthy ſeruant of his Godlines, goeth on in the whole Epiſtle to ſhewe the Iniuſtice of that Lawe, as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth: And in the end concludes his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle with theſe wordes; <hi>I being ſubiect to</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:22043:14"/>
               <hi>your command haue cauſed the ſame lawe to bee ſent through diuers parts of your Dominions: and becauſe the lawe it ſelfe doeth not agree to the Law of the Almightie God, I haue ſignified the ſame by my Letters to your moſt excellent Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: ſo that on both parts I haue payed what I ought, becauſe I haue yeelded Obedience to the Emperour, and haue not holden my peace, in what I thought for God.</hi> Now how great a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie there is betwixt this ancient Popes acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in obeying an Emperour by the publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Decree, which in his owne Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he thought vnlawfull, and this preſent Popes prohibition to a Kings Subiects from Obedience vnto him in things moſt lawfull and meere Temporall; I remit it to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders indifferency. And anſwerably to the Fathers ſpake the Councels in their decrees. As the Councell of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Arela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe ſub Carolo Can.</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>Arles,</hi> ſubmitting the whole Councell to the Emperour in theſe words: <hi>Theſe things wee haue decreed to bee preſented to the Emperour, beſeeching his Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, that if we haue done leſse then we ought, it may be ſupplied by his wiſedome: if any thing otherwiſe then reaſon require, it may bee corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:22043:15"/>
               <hi>by his iudgement: if any thing bee well ſet downe of vs, it may be perfected by his aide and aſsiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why ſhould I ſpeake of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, To whom not one Councell, but ſixe ſeuerall Councels, <hi>Franckford, Arles, Towers, Shallons, Mentz,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rhemes</hi> did who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit themſelues? And not rather ſpeake of all the generall Councels, that of <hi>Nice, Conſtantinople, Epheſus, Calcedon,</hi> and the foure other commonly ſo reputed, which did ſubmit themſelues to the Emperors wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and Piety in all things? Inſomuch as that of <hi>Epheſus</hi> repeated it foure ſeuerall times, <hi>That they were ſummoned by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Oracle, becke, charge and command, and betooke themſelues to his godlineſſe,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Vide epiſtolam generalis Con: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>beſeeching him, that the decrees made against</hi> Neſtorius <hi>and his followers, might by his power haue their full force and validitie,</hi> as appeareth manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Epiſtle of the generall Councell of <hi>Epheſus</hi> written <hi>ad Auguſtos.</hi> I alſo reade that Chriſt ſaid, <hi>his</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 18. 36</note> 
               <hi>kingdom was not of this world,</hi> bidding, <hi>Giue to</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 22. 21</note> Caeſar <hi>what was</hi> Caeſars, <hi>and to God what was Gods.</hi> And I euer held
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22043:15"/>
it for an infallible Maxime in Diuinity, That temporall Obedience to a Temporall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate did nothing repugne to matters of Faith or ſaluation of ſoules. But that euer temporall Obedience was againſt Faith and ſaluation of ſoules, as in this <hi>Breue</hi> is allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, was neuer before heard nor read of in the Chriſtian Church; and therefore I would haue wiſhed the Pope, before hee had ſet downe this Commaundement to all Papiſts here, That ſince in him is the Power, by the infallibility of his ſpirit, to make new Articles of Faith when euer it ſhall pleaſe him; That he had firſt ſet it down for an article of faith, before he had commanded all Catholikes to beleeue and obey it. I will then conclude the Anſwere to this point in a <hi>Dilemma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Either it is lawfull to obey the Soueraigne <note place="margin">Queſtion.</note> in Temporall things, or not.</p>
            <p>If it be lawfull, (as I neuer heard nor read <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> it doubted of) Then why is he ſo vniuſt, and ſo cruell towards his owne Catholikes, as to Commaund them to diſobey their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes lawfull Commandement?</p>
            <p>If it be vnlawfull, Why hath he neither expreſſed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:22043:16"/>
or any other, that either would profeſſe, or any wayes tollerate the profeſſors of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; contrary to his manifold vowes and proteſtations, <hi>ſimul &amp; eodem tempore,</hi> and as it were deliuered <hi>vno &amp; eodem ſpiritu,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of his Maieſties miniſters abroad, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsing ſuch kindneſſe, and ſhewing ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe to aduance him to this Crowne. Nay, the moſt part of Catholikes here, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this <hi>Breue</hi> when it came to their hands, to be ſo farre againſt Diuinitie, Policy, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſenſe, were firmely perſwaded, that it was but a counterfeit Libel deuiſed in hatred <note place="margin">The Catholikes opinion of the Breue.</note> of the <hi>Pope;</hi> Or at the fartheſt, a thing haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done vpon wrong Information, as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid. Of which opinion were not onely the ſimpler ſort of Papiſts, but euen ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them of beſt account, both for lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and experience; wherof the Archprieſt himſelfe was one. But for ſoluing of this obiection, the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe hath taken new paines, by ſending forth a ſecond <hi>Breue,</hi> only for giuing faith and confirmation to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: That whereas before, his ſinne might haue bene thought to haue proceeded from
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22043:16"/>
raſhneſſe and miſ-information, he will now wilfully and willingly double the ſame: whereof the Copie followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="popes_letter">
            <head>
               <hi>TO OVR BELO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonnes the Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> Paulus P. P. V<hi rend="sup">tus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued Sonnes, Salutation and <note place="margin">The ſecond Breue.</note> Apoſtolicall Benediction. It is reported vnto vs, that there are found certayne men amongst you, who when as wee haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently declared by our Letters, dated the laſt yeere on the tenth of the Calends of October in the forme of a <hi>Breue,</hi> that ye cannot with ſafe Conſcience take the Oath, which was then requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of you; And when as wee haue further ſtraightly required you, that by no meanes yee ſhould take it; yet there are ſome, I ſay, among you, which dare now affirme, That ſuch Letters
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:22043:17"/>
            <head>THE ANSWERE TO the ſecond <hi>Breue.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow for this <hi>Breue,</hi> I may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reflect his owne phraſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, in tearming it to be <hi>the craft of the Deuil.</hi> For if the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill had ſtudied a thouſand yeeres for to find out a miſchiefe for our Catholikes, here hee hath found it in this, That now when many Catholikes haue taken their Oath, and ſome Prieſts alſo; yea, the Arch-prieſt himſelfe, without compunction or ſticking, they ſhall not now onely bee bound to refuſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of their naturall Allegiance to their Soueraigne, which might yet haue bin ſome way coloured vpon diuers ſcruples concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon the words of the Oath; but they muſt now renounce and forſweare their profeſsion of obedience already ſworne, and ſo muſt, as it were at the third Inſtance, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare <note place="margin">A double Oath of every Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</note>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:22043:17"/>
their two former Oaths, firſt cloſely ſworne by their birth in their naturall Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance; and next, clearely confirmed by this Oath, which doeth nothing but expreſſe the ſame; So as no man can now hold the faith, or procure the Saluation of his ſoule in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that muſt not abiure and renounce his borne and ſworne Allegiance to his naturall Soueraigne.</p>
            <p>And yet it is not ſufficient to ratifie the laſt yeeres <hi>Breue</hi> by a new one come forth this yeere; But (that not onely euery yeere, but euery moneth may produce a new Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) The great and famous writer of the Controuerſies, The late Vn-Ieſuited Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> muſt adde his talent to this good worke, by blowing the Bellowes of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and ſharpening the Spurre to Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, by ſending ſuch a Letter of his to the Arch-prieſt here, as it is a wonder how Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and an Ambitious deſire of maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that Monarchy, ſhould charme the wits of ſo famouſly learned a man.</p>
            <p>The Copie whereof here followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:22043:18"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST Reuerend Maſter GEORGE BLACKVVEL Arch-prieſt of the Engliſh: <hi>Robert of the holy Church of Rome</hi> Cardinall BELLARMIN, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth greeting.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost reuerend Sir, and Brother in Christ, It is almost fourtie yeeres ſince we did ſee one the other: But yet I haue neuer beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of our ancient acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, neither haue I ceaſed, ſeeing I could doe you no other good, to commend your labouring moſt painefully in the Lordes vineyard, in my prayers to God. And I doubt not, but that I haue liued all this while in your memorie, and haue had ſome place in your prayers at the Lords Altar. So therefore euen vnto this time wee haue abidden, as</hi> S. Iohn <hi>ſpeaketh, in the mutuall loue one of the other, not by worde or letter, but by labour and trueth. But a late meſsage which</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:22043:18"/>
               <hi>was brought vnto vs within a few dayes, of your bonds and impriſonment, hath inforced mee to breake off this ſilence; which meſſage, although it ſeemed heauie in regard of the loſse of your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall function which you haue exerciſed in that Church, yet withall it ſeemed ioyous, becauſe you drew neere vnto the glory of</hi> Martyrdome, <hi>then the which thing there is no gift of God more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie; That you, who haue fed your Flocke ſo many yeeres with the worde and doctrine, ſhould now feed it more gloriouſly by the example of your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. But another heauy tidings did not a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle diſquiet and almoſt take away this ioy, which immediatly followed, of the aduerſaries aſſault, and peraduenture of the ſlip and fall of your Conſtancie, in refuſing an vnlawfull Oath. Neither truely (most deare brother) could that oath therefore be lawfull, becauſe it was offered in ſort tempered and modified: for you knowe that thoſe kinde of modifications are nothing els, but ſleights and ſubtilties of Satan, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique faith touching the Primacie of the Sea Apoſtolike, might either ſecretly or openly be ſhot at, for the which faith ſo many worthy Martyrs euen in that very</hi> England <hi>it ſelfe, haue reſi</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:22043:19"/>
               <hi>ſted vnto blood. For moſt certaine it is, that in whatſoeuer words the Oath is conceiued by the aduerſaries of the faith in that Kingdome, it tends to this end, that the Authoritie of the head of the Church in</hi> England, <hi>may bee transferred from the ſucceſsour of S.</hi> Peter, <hi>to the Succeſſour of K.</hi> Henry <hi>the eight. For that which is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the danger of the Kings life, if the high Prieſt ſhould haue the ſame power in</hi> England, <hi>which he hath in all other Chriſtian Kingdomes, it is altogether idle, as all that haue any vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, may eaſily perceiue. For it was neuer heard of from the Churches infancie vntill this day, that euer any</hi> Pope <hi>did command, that any Prince, though an Heretike, though an Ethnike, though a Perſecuter, ſhould be murdered, or did approue of the fact, when it was done by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And why, I pray you, doeth onely the King of</hi> England <hi>feare that, which none of all other the Princes in Chriſtendome either doeth feare, or euer did feare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But, as I ſayd, theſe vaine pretexts are but the Trappes and Stratagemes of Sathan: Of which kind, I could produce not a few out of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Stories, if I went about to write a booke, and</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:22043:19"/>
               <hi>not an Epiſtle. One only for example ſake, I will call to your memory.</hi> S. Gregorius Nazianze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus <hi>in his firſt Oration againſt</hi> Iulian <hi>the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, reporteth, That he, the more eaſily to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile the ſimple Chriſtians, did inſert the Images of the falſe gods into the pictures of the Emperor, which the Romanes did vſe to bow downe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to with a ciuill kind of reuerence; ſo that no man could doe reuerence to the Emperours picture, but withall he muſt adore the Images of the falſe gods: Whereupon it came to paſse, that many were deceiued. And if there were any that found out the Emperours craft, and refuſed to worſhip his picture, thoſe were most grieuouſly puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as men that had contemned the Emperour in his Image. Some ſuch like thing, me thinkes, I ſee in the Oath that is offered to you, which is ſo craftily compoſed, that no man can deteſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt the King, and make profeſsion of his Ciuill ſubiection, but he muſt be conſtrayned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſly to denie the Primacie of the Apoſtolike Sea. But the ſeruants of Chriſt, and eſpecially the chiefe Prieſts of the Lord ought to be ſo farre from taking an vnlawfull Oath, where they may indamage their Faith, that they ought to beware that</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:22043:20"/>
ry <hi>the Great hath written, in his</hi> 42. <hi>Epistle of his</hi> 11. <hi>booke.</hi> Let not the Reuerence due to the Apoſtolique Sea, bee troubled by any mans preſumption: for then the ſtate of the members doeth remaine entire, when the head of the faith is not bruiſed by any iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. <hi>Therefore, by S.</hi> Gregories <hi>testimonie, when they are buſie about diſturbing or dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, or taking away of the Primacie of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolique Sea, then are they buſie about cutting off the very head of the faith, and diſsoluing of the ſtate of the whole body, and of all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Which ſelfe ſame thing S.</hi> Leo <hi>doeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme in his third Sermon of his Aſſumption to the</hi> Pope-dome, <hi>when he ſaith,</hi> Our Lord had a ſpeciall care of <hi>Peter,</hi> and prayed properly for <hi>Peters</hi> faith, as though the ſtate of others were more ſtable, when their Princes minde was not to be ouercome. <hi>Whereupon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his Epiſtle to the Biſhop of</hi> Vienna, <hi>doth not doubt to affirme,</hi> That he is not partaker of the Diuine Myſterie, that dare depart from the ſoliditie of <hi>Peter: who alſo ſaith,</hi> That hee who thinketh the Primacie to bee denied to that Sea, hee can in no ſort leſſen
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22043:20"/>
the Authoritie of it, but by being puft vp with the ſpirit of pride, doeth caſt himſelfe headlong into hell. <hi>Theſe and many other of this kinde, I am very ſure are moſt familiar to you: who beſides many other bookes, haue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently read ouer the viſible Monarchie of your owne</hi> Saunders, <hi>a moſt diligent writer, and one who hath worthily deſerued of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Neither can you be ignorant, that moſt holy and learned men,</hi> Iohn <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>and</hi> Thomas More <hi>within our memorie, for this one moſt weightie head of doctrine, ledde the way to</hi> Martyrdome <hi>to many others, to the exceeding glory of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Nation. But I would put you in remembrance that you ſhould take heart, and conſidering the weightineſſe of the cauſe, not to truſt too much to your owne iudgement, neither be wiſe aboue that is meete to bee wiſe: And if peraduenture your fall haue proceeded not vpon want of conſideration, but through humane infirmitie, and for feare of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and impriſonment; yet doe not preferre a temporall libertie to the libertie of the glory of the Sonnes of God, neither for eſcaping a light and momentanie tribulation, looſe an eternall waight</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:22043:21"/>
world to wonder with me, at the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſo groſſe an Errour by ſo learned a man, as that hee ſhould haue pained him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to haue ſet downe ſo elaborate a Letter, for the refutation of a quite miſtaken Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. For it appeareth, that our Engliſh Fugitiues, of whoſe inward ſocietie with him he ſo greatly vaunteth, haue ſo faſt hamme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his head the Oath of Supremacie, which hath euer bene ſo great a Scarre vnto them, as hee thinking by his Letter to haue refuted the laſt Oath, hath in place thereof onely payd the Oath of Supremacie, which was moſt in his head; As a man that being earneſtly caried in his thoughts vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter then hee is preſently in doing, will often name the matter, or perſon hee is thinking of, in place of the other thing hee hath at that time in hand.</p>
            <p>For, as the Oath of Supremacy was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed for putting a difference betweene Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and them of our profeſsion: So was this Oath, which hee would ſeeme to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne, <note place="margin">The difference betweene the Oath of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, and this of Allegiance.</note> ordained for making a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Ciuilly obedient Papiſts, and the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22043:21"/>
peruerſe Diſciples of the Powder-Treaſon. Yet doth all his Letter runne vpon an Inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue againſt the compulſion of Catholikes to denie the authoritie of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and in place thereof to acknowledge the ſucceſſors of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight. For, in King <hi>Henry</hi> the eights time was the Oath of Supremacie firſt made: By him were <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> and <hi>Roffenſis</hi> put to death, partly for refuſing of it. From his time till now haue all our Princes profeſsing this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſucceſsiuely in effect mainteined the ſame: And in that Oath only is conteined the Kings abſolute power to bee Iudge ouer all perſons aſwell Ciuill as Eccleſiaſticall, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all forreigne Powers and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates to be Iudges within his Dominions; Whereas this laſt made Oath containeth no ſuch matter, onely medling with the Ciuill Obedience of Subiects to their Soueraigne, in meere Temporall cauſes.</p>
            <p>And that it may the better appeare, that whereas by name hee ſeemeth to condemne the laſt Oath; yet indeede his whole letter runneth vpon nothing, but vpon the
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:22043:22"/>
ſome other authority of the Church and Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet by other meanes with others helpe he may depoſe our King.</p>
            <p>That the Pope may diſpoſe of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Kingdomes and Dominions.</p>
            <p>That the Pope may giue authoritie to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſome Forrein Prince to inuade his Maieſties Dominions.</p>
            <p>That the Pope may diſcharge his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> of their Allegiance and Obedience to his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>That the Pope may giue Licence to one <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> or more of his Maieſties Subiects to beare Armes againſt his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>That the Pope may giue leaue to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> King his Subiects to offer violence to his Maieſties ſacred perſon, or to his Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to ſome of his Subiects.</p>
            <p>That if the Pope ſhall by Sentence Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> or depoſe our King, his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects are not to beare Faith and Allegiance to his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>If the Pope ſhall by Sentence Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate or depoſe his Maieſty, his Subiects are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> not bound to defend with all their power
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22043:22"/>
his Maieſties Perſon and Crowne.</p>
            <p>If the Pope ſhall giue out any Sentence <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> of Excommunication, or Depriuation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, the Subiects by reaſon of that Sentence, are not bound to reueile all Conſpiracies &amp; Treaſons againſt the King, which ſhal come to their hearing and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>That it is not Hereticall and deteſtable to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> holde, that Princes being Excommunicated by the Pope, may be either depoſed, or killed by their Subiects, or any other.</p>
            <p>That the Pope hath power to abſolue his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Maieſties Subiects from this oath, or from ſome part thereof.</p>
            <p>That this oath is not adminiſtred to his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> Maieſties Subiects, by a full and lawfull Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</p>
            <p>That this oath is to be taken with Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> mentall euaſion, or ſecret reſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not with the heart and good will, ſincerely in the true faith of a Chriſtian man.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the true and naturall branches of the body of this Oath. The affirmatiue of all which Negatiues doe neither concerne
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22043:23"/>
in any caſe the <hi>Popes</hi> Supremacie in ſpirituall cauſes, nor yet were euer concluded, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by any complete generall Councell to <note place="margin">Touching the pretended coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Later: See Plat. <hi>In vita in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocen.</hi> 3.</note> belong to the <hi>Popes</hi> Authoritie: and their owne ſchoole Doctours are at irreconcilable oddes and iarres about them.</p>
            <p>And that the world may yet farther ſee, his Maieſties and whole States ſetting downe of this oath, did not proceed from any new inuention of theirs, but as it is warranted by the word of God: ſo doth it take the example <note place="margin">The oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Councels.</note> from an oath of Allegiance decreed a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres agone, which a famous Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel then, together with diuers other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, were ſo farre from condemning, (as the <hi>Pope</hi> now hath done this oath) as I haue thought good to ſet down their owne words here in that purpoſe, wherby it may appeare that his Maieſtie craueth nothing now of his Subiects in this Oath, which was not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and carefully commanded then by the Councels to be obeyed without exception of perſons. Nay not in the very particular poynt of <hi>Equiuocation,</hi> which his Maieſtie in this oath is ſo carefull to haue eſchewed: but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22043:23"/>
you ſhall here ſee the ſaid Councels in their <note place="margin">The ancient Councels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation.</note> decrees, as careful to prouide for the eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame, ſo as almoſt euery poynt of that Action, and this of ours, ſhall be found to haue relation and agreeance one with the other, ſaue onely in this, that thoſe olde Councels were carefull and ſtrait in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding <note place="margin">The difference between the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Councels and the Popes counſelling of the Catholikes.</note> the taking of the ſame: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by the contrary, hee that now vaunteth himſelfe to be head of all Councels, is as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſtrait in the prohibition of all men from the taking of this Oath of Allegiance.</p>
            <p>The wordes of the Councell bee theſe. <hi>Heare our Sentence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoeuer of vs, or of all the people thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Toletan.</hi> 4. <hi>can.</hi> 74.</note> 
               <hi>all</hi> Spaine, <hi>ſhall violate the Oath of his fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, which he hath giuen for the preſeruation of his Countrey, or of the Kings Perſon, or ſhall go about by any Conſpiracy or endeuour to touch the life of the King, or ſhall vſurpe by any power or Tyrannicall preſumption the Soueraigntie of the Kingdome, let him be accurſed in the ſight of God the Father, and of his Angels, and be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den an Alien from the Catholike Church, which he hath profaned by his periury; together with all</hi>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:22043:24"/>
               <hi>Fidelitie in their mouthes; when they holde an impious perfidiouſneſſe in their mindes.</hi> And <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Tolc.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 75.</note> againe, <hi>They ſweare to their Kings, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they may preuaricate in the fidelitie which they haue promiſed. Neither doe they feare the volume of Gods Iudgement, in the which the curſe of God is threatned vpon them, which doe ſweare in the Name of God deceitfully.</hi> To the like effect ſpake they in the Councell of <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Aquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gran. ſub Ludou. Pio &amp; Greg.</hi> 4. <hi>can.</hi> 12. <hi>anno</hi> 836.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſgran, That whoſoeuer, from the higheſt to the loweſt of the Cleargie, ſhall make defection from the Orthodoxe Emperour</hi> Lodowicke, <hi>or ſhall violate the Oath of Fidelitie made vnto him, or ſhall adhere to his Enemies; let him bee depriued of all Honour and Dignitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to come to a particular anſwere of his Letter. Firſt as concerning the ſweet memorie hee hath of his old acquaintance with the Arch-prieſt; it may indeed be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for him to recount: But ſure I am, his acquaintance with him, and the reſt of his ſocietie our Fugitiues, (whereof he alſo van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe in his preface to the reader, in his booke of Controuerſies) hath prooued ſowre to vs and our State. For ſome of ſuch
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22043:24"/>
Prieſts and Ieſuites as were the greateſt Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and Fomenters of the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt her late Maieſtie, gaue vp Father <hi>Robert</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Campion &amp; Hart. See the conference in the Tower.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> for one of their greateſt authorities and oracles. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I doe not enuie the great honour hee can winne by his vaunt of his inward famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aritie with an other Princes Traitours, and Fugitiues: whom vnto, if he teach no better maners, then hitherto he hath done, I thinke his Fellowſhip are little beholding vnto him.</p>
            <p>And for deſiring him to remember him in his prayers at the altar of the Lord: If the Arch prieſts prayers proue no more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his ſoule, then <hi>Bellarmines</hi> counſell is like to proue profitable both to the ſoule and body of <hi>Blackwell</hi> (if he would followe it;) the authour of this letter might very well be without his prayers.</p>
            <p>Now the firſt meſſenger that I can finde, which brought ioyfull newes of the Arch-prieſt to <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> was he that brought the newes of the Arch-prieſtes taking, and firſt appearance of <hi>Martyrdome.</hi> A great ſigne ſurely of the Cardinals mortification, that he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:22043:25"/>
was ſo reioyced to heare of the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, impriſonment, and appearance of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to death, of ſo old and deare a friend of his. But yet apparantly he ſhould firſt haue bene ſure, that he was onely to be puniſhed for cauſe of Religion, before hee had ſo tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed vpon the expectation of his <hi>Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> For firſt, by what rule of Charitie was <note place="margin">The Cardinals charitie.</note> it lawfull for him to iudge the King our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne a Perſecutour, before proofe had bene made of it, by the ſaide Arch-prieſtes condemnation and death? What could hee know, That the ſaid Arch-prieſt was not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpon ſuſpition of his guiltineſſe in the Powder-treaſon? What certaine information had he then receiued vpon the particulars, whereupon he was to be accuſed? And laſt of all, by what inſpiration could he foretell whereupon hee was to be accuſed? For at that time there was yet nothing laide to his charge. And if Charitie ſhould not be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitious, what warrant had hee abſolutely to condemne our Soueraigne of vſing perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and tyrannie, which could not but bee implied vpon his Maieſtie, if <hi>Blackwell</hi> was
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:22043:25"/>
to be a Martyr? But ſurely it may iuſtly bee ſaid of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in this caſe, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour CHRIST ſaith of all worldly and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men, who thinke it enough to loue their <note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 5. 43.</note> friends, and hate their enemies; the limits of the Cardinals charitie extending no farther, then to them of his owne profeſsion. For what euer he added in ſuperfluous charitie to <hi>Blackwell</hi> in reioycing in the ſpeculation of his future <hi>Martyrdome,</hi> hee detracted as much vniuſtly and vncharitably from his Maieſtie our Soueraigne, in accounting of him thereby as of a bloody perſecutour. And whereas this ioy of his was interrupted by the next meſſenger, that brought the newes of the ſaid Arch-prieſt his failing in his Conſtancie by taking of this Oath; hee needed neuer to haue bene troubled, either with his former ioy, or his ſecond ſorrowe, both being alike falſly grounded. For as it was neuer his Maieſties intention to lay any thing vnto the ſaid Arch-prieſts charge, as he hath neuer done to any, for cauſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; So was <hi>Blackwels</hi> conſtancie neuer brangled by taking of this Oath; It being
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:22043:26"/>
a thing, which hee euer thought lawfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his apprehenſion, and whereunto hee perſwaded all Catholikes to giue obedience; like as after his apprehenſion, he neuer made doubt, nor ſtop in it, but at the firſt offering it vnto him, did freely take it, as a thing moſt lawfull; Neither meanes of threatning, or flatterie, being euer vſed vnto him, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe can yet beare witneſſe.</p>
            <p>And as for the temperature and modifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this Oath, Except that a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and lawfull matter is there ſet downe in reaſonable and temperate wordes agreeing thereunto; I know not what he can meane, by quarrelling it for that fault. For no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratneſſe nor modifications in words there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, can iuſtly be called the deuils craft, when the thing it ſelfe is ſo plaine, and ſo plainely interpreted to all them that take it, as the only troubleſome thing in it all, be the words vſed in the ende thereof, for eſchewing <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocation</hi> and mentall reſeruation; which newe Catholique doctrine may farre iuſtlier be called the deuils craft, then any plaine and temperate words, in ſo plaine and cleare
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22043:26"/>
a matter. But what ſhall wee ſay of theſe ſtrange <hi>Agrestes,</hi> whome of with the <hi>Satyre</hi> we may iuſtly complaine, that they blowe both hote and cold out of one mouth? For <hi>Luther</hi> and all our bolde and free ſpeaking writers, are mightily railed vpon by them, as hot brained fellowes, and ſpeakers by the deuils inſtinct: And now if we ſpeake mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately and temperately of them, it muſt be termed the deuils craft. And therefore wee may iuſtly complaine with CHRIST, that when wee <note n="a" place="margin">Matt. 11. 17.</note> mourne, they will not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and when we pipe, they wil not dance. But neither <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> his ſeueritie, nor CHRIST his meekeneſſe and lenitie can pleaſe them, who builde but to their owne Monarchie, vpon the ground of their owne traditions, and not to CHRIST, vpon the ground of his Word and infallible Trueth.</p>
            <p>But what can bee meant by alleadging, That the craft of the deuill herein is onely vſed for ſubuerſion of the Catholike Faith, and euerſion of S. <hi>Peters</hi> Primacy, had need be commented anew by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf. For in all this Letter of his, neuer one word
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:22043:27"/>
is vſed to prooue, that by any part of this Oath the primacie of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is any way medled with, except Maſter <hi>Bellarmine</hi> his bare alledging; which without prouing it by more cleare demonſtration, can neuer ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the conſcience of any reaſonable man. For, for ought that I knowe, Heauen and Earth are no farther aſunder, then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of a Temporall obedience to a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall King, is different from any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Catholike Faith, or Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> For, as for the Catholike <note place="margin">No deciſion of any point of Religion in the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</note> Faith, can there bee one word found in all that Oath, tending or ſounding to matter of Religion? Doeth he that taketh it, promiſe there to beleeue, or not to beleeue any Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Religion? Or doeth hee ſo much as name a true or a falſe Church there? And as for Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Primacy, I know no Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles name that is therein named, but the name of our Soueraigne <hi>Iames,</hi> though it pleaſe him not to deigne to name him in all the Letter, albeit the contents thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne him in the higheſt degree. Neither is there any mention at all made therein, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:22043:27"/>
               <hi>conceptis verbis,</hi> or by any other indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect meanes, either of the Hierarchy of the Church, of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſsion, of the Sea Apoſtolike, or of any ſuch matter: But that the Author of our Letter doeth brauely make mention of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſsion, bringing it in compariſon with the ſucceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight. Of which vnapt and vnmannerly Similitude, I wonder he ſhould not bee much aſhamed. For, as our King <hi>Henries</hi> ſucceſſour, whom by he meaneth, neuer did, nor will preſume to create any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith, or to be Iudge thereof, but to ſubmit his exemplary obedience vnto them, in as great humilitie, as the meaneſt of the land; So if the Pope could bee as well able <note place="margin">Farre more eaſie to proue his Maieſties ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion from his Auceſtors, then the Pope from <hi>S. Peter.</hi>
               </note> to prooue his, either Perſonall, or Doctrinall ſucceſsion from <hi>S. Peter,</hi> as hee is able to proue his lineall deſcent from the Kings of England and Scotland, there had neuer bene ſo long adoe, nor ſo much ſturre kept about this Queſtion in Chriſtendome; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bella<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de Rom Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. lib.</hi> 4 <hi>cap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llar de Rom Pontif. lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>M. Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe needed to haue beſtowed ſo many ſheetes of paper, <hi>De ſummo Pontifice</hi> in his great Bookes of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:22043:28"/>
Controuerſies: And when all is done, to conclude with a morall certitude, and a <hi>pie credendum,</hi> bringing in the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> Popes, that are parties in this cauſe, to be his witneſſes: And yet their Hiſtoricall Narration muſt be no Article of Faith. And ſure we are, that his Maieſtie our Soueraigne, doeth vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly imitate the worthy Actions of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors; In whom their Vertues doe more brightly ſhine, then can be well proued the Popes in our age to be <hi>ſimiles Petro,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in curſing of Kings, and ſetting free their Subiects from their Allegiance vnto them.</p>
            <p>But now we come to his ſtrongeſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which is, That he would alledge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Soueraigne a Panick terrour, as if he were poſſeſſed with a needeleſſe feare. <hi>For,</hi> ſaith the Cardinall, <hi>from the beginning of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Cardinals waightieſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</note> 
               <hi>Church his firſt Infancie, euen to this day, where was it euer heard, that euer a Pope either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be killed, or allowed the ſlaughter of any Prince whatſoeuer, whether he were an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, an Ethnike, or Perſecutor?</hi> But firſt, wherefore doth he here wilfully, and of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe omit the reſt of the points mentioned
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:22043:28"/>
in that Oath, for depoſing, degrading, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp of Armes, or Rebelling againſt them, which are as well mentioned in that Oath, as the killing of them? As being all of one conſequence againſt a King, no Subiect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſcrupulous, as that he will attempt the one, and leaue the other vnperformed if he can. And yet ſurely I cannot blame him for paſsing it ouer, ſince he could not otherwiſe haue eſchewed the direct belying of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in tearmes, which he now doeth but in ſubſtance and effect. For <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Rom. Pontif lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> as for the Popes depoſing and degrading of Kings, hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſo braue vaunts and bragges of it in his former Bookes, as he could neuer with ciuill honeſtie haue denyed it here.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the Popes allowing of killing of Kings, I know not with what face he can ſet ſo ſtout a denyall vpon it againſt his owne knowledge. How many Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors did the Pope raiſe warre againſt in their owne bowels? Who as they were ouercome in battayle, were ſubiect to haue bene killed therein; which I hope the Pope could not but haue allowed, when hee was ſo farre
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:22043:29"/>
inraged at <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Platina &amp; Cusp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nus in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Henrici</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth for giuing buriall to his fathers dead corps, after the Pope had ſtirred him vp to rebell againſt his father, and procured his ruine. But leauing theſe olde Hiſtories to <hi>Bellarmines</hi> owne bookes, that doe moſt authentically cite them, as I haue already ſaid, let vs turne our eyes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our owne time, and therein remember what a Panegyrik <note n="c" place="margin">See the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> made in the Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vpon the death of <hi>Henry</hi> the 3.</note> oration was made by the Pope, in praiſe and approbation of the Frier and his fact, that murthered King <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France,</hi> who was ſo farre from ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being Heretike, Ethnike, or Perſecutor in their account, that the ſaid Popes owne wordes in that Oration are, <hi>That a true Frier had killed a counterfeit Frier.</hi> And beſides that vehement Oration, and congratulation for that fact, how neere it ſcaped, that the ſaid Frier was not Canonized for that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Acte, is better knowen to <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and his followers, then to vs here.</p>
            <p>But ſure I am, if ſome Cardinals had not beene more wiſe and circumſpect in that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, then the Pope himſelfe was, the Popes owne Calender of his Saints would haue
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:22043:29"/>
ſufficiently proued <hi>Bellarmine</hi> a lyar in this caſe. And to drawe yet neerer vnto our ſelues; How many Practiſes and Attempts were made againſt the late Queene our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes life, which were directly inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to thoſe Traytors by their Confeſſors, and plainly authorized by the Popes allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? For verification whereof, there needes no more proofe, then that neuer Pope either then or ſince, called any Church-man in queſtion for medling in thoſe Treaſonable conſpiracies; Nay, the Cardinals owne <hi>S. Sanderus</hi> mentioned in his Letter, coulde well verifie this trueth, if he were aliue; and who wil looke his books, wil find them filled with no other Doctrine then this. And what difference there is betweene the killing or allowing the ſlaughter of Kings, and the ſtirring vp and approbation of practiſes to kill them, I remit to <hi>Bellarmines</hi> owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It may then very clearely appeare, how ſtrangely this Authours paſsion hath made him forget himſelfe, by implicating himſelfe in ſo ſtrong a Contradiction againſt his owne knowledge and conſcience, againſt the
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:22043:30"/>
               <hi>the end that theeues might afterward take it from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecllar. de Pont. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> Peter <hi>did not looſe that righteouſneſse that was in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contrary, <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Iuſt lib</hi> 2 <hi>cap</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Peters ſinne was deadly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Antichriſt ſhall be a Magitian, and after the maner of other Magitians ſhall ſecretly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the deuill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid ex ſenten. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pol. &amp; Cyrilli &amp; cap.</hi> 12 <hi>eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m libri.</hi>
               </note> Contrary, <hi>He ſhal not admit of idolatrie: he ſhall hate idoles, and reedifie the Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the words of</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de miſſa cap.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>Conſecration the true and ſolemne Oblation is made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contrary, <hi>The</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de miſs lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Oblation is not made by the wordes, but doeth conſiſt in the offering of the thing it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar de anim. Chriſt. lib.</hi> 4 <hi>cap</hi> 5</note> 
               <hi>That the ende of the world cannot bee knowen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Pont. lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</note> Contrary, <hi>After the death of Antichriſt, there ſhall bee but fiue and fortie dayes till the end of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Pont. lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>That the tenne Kings ſhal burne the ſcarlet whore, that is, Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Bellar. ibidem.</note> Contrary, <hi>Antichrist ſhal hate Rome, and fight againſt it, and burne it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar de Pont. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>The name of vniuerſall Biſhop may bee</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:22043:30"/>
               <hi>vnderſtood two wayes; One way, that he which is ſaid to be vniuerſall Biſhop, may be thought to be the onely Biſhop; ſo that all other Biſhops are but onely his Vicars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contrary, <hi>All ordinarie</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Pon. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Iuriſdiction of Biſhops doth deſcend immediatly from the</hi> Pope. Which few places I haue onely ſelected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many the like, that the diſcreete and iudicious Reader may diſcerne <hi>Ex vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue Leonem.</hi> For when euer hee is preſſed with a weighty Obiection, he neuer careth, nor remembreth how his Solution and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to that, may make him gaineſay his owne Doctrine in ſome other places, ſo it ſerue him for a ſhift to put off the preſent ſtorme withall.</p>
            <p>But now to returne to our matter againe. <hi>Since Popes,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>haue neuer at any time medled againſt Kings, Wherefore, I pray you, ſhould onely the King of</hi> England <hi>bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of that, whereof neuer Chriſtian King is, or was afraid?</hi> Was neuer Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour or King afraid of the Popes? How then were theſe miſerable Emperours toſt and turmoiled, and in the end vtterly ruined
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:22043:31"/>
by the Popes, for proofe whereof I haue already cited <hi>Bellarmines</hi> owne bookes? Was not the <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abbas Vſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen. Lam. Scafen. Anno</hi> 1077. <hi>Plat. in vit. Greg.</hi> 7.</note> Emperour afraid, who waited barefooted in the froſt &amp; ſnow three dayes at the Popes gate, before he could get entrie? Was not the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alfonſ. Ciacou. in vit. Alex.</hi> 3. <hi>Geneb. Chronol.</hi>
               </note> Emperor alſo afraid, who was driuen to lie agroofe on his belly, and ſuffer another Pope to tread vpon his necke? And was not another <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ranulph. in Polychronicon. lib.</hi> 7.</note> Emperour afraid, who was conſtrained in like maner to indure a third Pope to beate off from his head the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Crowne with his foote? Was not <note n="d" place="margin">Abbas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſperg.</note> 
               <hi>Philip</hi> afraid, being made Emperour againſt Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thirds good liking, when he brake out into theſe words, <hi>Either the Pope ſhall take the Crowne from</hi> Philip, <hi>or</hi> Philip <hi>ſhall take the Miter from the Pope?</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Pope ſtirred vp <hi>Otho</hi> againſt him, who ſlew him, and preſently went to <hi>Rome,</hi> and was crowned Emperour by the Pope, though afterward the Pope depoſed him too. Was not the Emperour <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Petrus de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Cuſpian in vit. Frederici. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Frederike</hi> aſraid, when <hi>Innocentius</hi> the fourth excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him, depriued him of his Crown, abſolued Princes of their Oath of Fidelity to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:22043:31"/>
him, and in <hi>Apulia</hi> corrupted one to giue him poiſon? Whereof the Emperour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couering, he hired one <hi>Manfredus</hi> to poiſon him; whereof he died. What did <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paulus Ionius Hiſt. lib.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the third write to the <hi>Soldan,</hi> That if hee would liue quietly, hee ſhould by ſome ſleight murther the Emperour? And to that end ſent him the Emperours picture. And not <note n="g" place="margin">Cuſpianus.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt take of the Turke <hi>Baiazetes</hi> two hundred thouſand Crownes to kill his brother <hi>Gemen,</hi> or as ſome call him, <hi>Siſimus,</hi> whom hee helde Captiue at <hi>Rome?</hi> Did hee not accept of the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to poiſon the man, and had his pay? Was not our <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Honenden pag.</hi> 539.</note> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond afraid af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſlaughter of <hi>S. Becket,</hi> That beſides his going bare-footed in Pilgrimage, was whipped vp and downe the Chapter-houſe like a ſchoole-boy, and glad to eſcape ſo too? Had not the King of <hi>France</hi> his father reaſon to be afraid, when the <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gomecius de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ebus geſtis Fran. Ximenij Arch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is. Tolet. lib.</hi> 5.</note> Pope gaue away his Kingdome of <hi>Nauarre</hi> to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> whereof hee yet poſſeſſeth the beſt halfe? Had not the King his ſonne reaſon to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, when hee was forced to begge ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsiuely
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:22043:32"/>
the relaxation of his Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, as he was content likewiſe to ſuffer his Ambaſſadour to be whipped at <hi>Rome</hi> for penance? And had not our late Soueraigne reaſon to looke to her ſelfe, when ſhee was Excommunicated by <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects looſed from their Fidelitie and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance towards her, her Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> giuen to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and that famous fugitiue Diuine, honoured with the like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of a red Hat as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is, is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to publiſh in print an <note n="a" place="margin">Card. Allens anſwere to Stan. Let. Anno 1587</note> Apologie for <hi>Stanlies</hi> Treaſon, maintaining, That by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her Excommunication and Hereſie, it was not onely lawfull for any of her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, but euen they were bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to depriue her of any Strength, which lay in their power to doe? And whether it were Armies, Townes, or Fortreſſes of hers which they had in their handes, they were obliged to put them in the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> her enemies hands, She no more being the right owner of any thing? But albeit it bee true, That wiſe men are moued by the examples of others dangers to vſe Prouidence and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:22043:32"/>
caution, according to the olde prouerbe, <hi>Tum tua res agitur, paries cùm proximus ardet:</hi> yet his Maieſtie our Soueraigne was neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier ſummoned to vſe this caution, by the practiſe of it in his owne Perſon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by the ſending forth of theſe Buls, whereof I made mention already, for debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him from Entrie vnto this Crowne, and Kingdome. And next after his Entrie and full poſſeſsion thereof, by the horrible Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Treaſon, which ſhould haue bereft both him and his, both of Crowne and Life. And howſoeuer the Pope will ſeeme to cleare himſelfe of any allowance of the ſaid Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Treaſon; yet can it not be denied, that his principall Miniſters here, and his chiefe <hi>Mancipia</hi> the Ieſuites, were the plaine practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers thereof: For which the principall of them hath died confeſsing it, and others haue fled the Countrey for the Crime; yea, ſome of them gone into <hi>Italy:</hi> And yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe that fled out of this Countrey for it, nor yet <hi>Baldwine,</hi> who though he then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the Low-countryes, was of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in it, were euer called to account for it by
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:22043:33"/>
And whereas for illuſtration of this ſtrong Argument of his, hee hath brought in for a ſimilitude the hiſtorie of <note n="a" place="margin">Nazianzenus in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uliar. inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua prima.</note> 
               <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> his dealing with the Chriſtians, when as he ſtraited them, either to commit idolatrie, or to come within the compaſſe of treaſon: I would wiſh the Author to remember, that although a ſimilitude may bee permitted <hi>claudicare vno pede;</hi> yet this was a very ill choſen ſimilitude, which is lame both of <note place="margin">The diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> feete and handes, and euery member of the body. For I ſhall in few wordes proue, that it agreeth in no one point, ſaue one, with our purpoſe, which is, that <hi>Iulian</hi> was an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and our Soueraigne is a King. Firſt, <hi>Iulian</hi> was an <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> one that had renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the whole Chriſtian faith, which he had once profeſſed, and became an Ethnike a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, or rather an Atheiſt: Our Soueraigne is a Chriſtian, who neuer changed that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that he dranke in with his milke, nor euer was aſhamed of his profeſsion. <hi>Iulian</hi> dealt againſt Chriſtians onely for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of Chriſts cauſe: His Maieſtie in this caſe dealeth with his Subiects, only to make
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:22043:33"/>
a diſtinction betweene true Subiects and falſe hearted Traitours. <hi>Iulians</hi> ende was the ouerthrow of the Chriſtians: His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties end is, to maintaine Chriſtianitie in a peaceable gouernement. <hi>Iulians</hi> drift was to make them commit idolatrie: His Maieſties drift is, to make his Subiects to make open profeſsion of their naturall Allegiance, and ciuill Obedience. <hi>Iulians</hi> meanes whereby he went about it, was by craft, and inſnaring them before they were aware: His Maieſties courſe in this is plaine, cleare, and voide of all obſcuritie, neuer refuſing leaue to any that are required to take this Oath, to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die it at leiſure, and giuing them all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of it they can craue. But the greateſt diſsimilitude of all is in this: That <hi>Iulian</hi> preſſed them to commit idolatrie to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles and images: But his Maieſtie and all his Subiects of his profeſsion are ſo farre from guilt in this point, as wee are counted Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques by you, becauſe wee will not commit idolatrie. So as, in the maine point of all, is the greateſt contrarietie: For, <hi>Iulian</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Chriſtians becauſe they would not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:22043:34"/>
commit idolatrie; and yee count his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie a perſecutour, becauſe he will not admit idolatrie. So as to conclude this point, this old Poets ſentence may well bee applied to <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> in vſing ſo vnapt a ſimilitude, <hi>Perdere quos vult Iupiter, hos dementat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore his vncharitable conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion doth not rightly follow, <hi>That it ſeemeth vnto him, that ſome ſuch thing ſhould be ſubtilly or fraudulently included in this Oath;</hi> As if no man can deteſt Treaſon againſt the King, or profeſſe Ciuil ſubiection, except he renounce the Primacie of the Apoſtolike Sea. But how he hath ſuckt this apprehenſion out at his fingers ends, I cannot imagine: for ſure I am, as I haue oft ſaid, he neuer goeth about to proue it: And to anſwere an improbable imagination, is to fight againſt a vaniſhing ſhadow. It cannot be denied in deede, that many ſeruants of CHRIST, as well Prieſts as others, haue endured conſtantly all ſortes of Torments, and Death for the profeſsion of CHRIST: And therefore to all ſuch his examples, as he bringeth in for verifying the ſame, I neede not to giue him any other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:22043:34"/>
ſaue onely to remember him, that he playeth the part of a Sophiſter in all theſe his Examples of the conſtancie of Martyrs, euer taking <hi>Controuer ſum pro confeſſo,</hi> as if this our caſe were of the ſame nature.</p>
            <p>But yet that the Reader may the better diſcouer, not only how vnaptly his Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes are applied, but likewiſe how diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly he vſeth himſelfe in all his citations; I haue thought good to ſet downe the very places themſelues cited by him, together with a ſhort deduction of the true ſtate of thoſe particular Caſes: whereby, how little theſe Examples can touch our Caſe; nay by the contrary, how rightly their true ſenſe may bee vſed, as our owne weapons to be throwen backe vpon him that alleadgeth them, ſhall eaſily appeare. And firſt, for <note n="a" place="margin">2. <hi>Macchabees cap.</hi> 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>Eleazar.</hi> If the Arch-prieſt his ground of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing his Maieſties Oath, were as good as <hi>Eleazars</hi> was, to forbeare to eate the Swines <note place="margin">An anſwere to the Cardinals example of <hi>Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar.</hi>
               </note> fleſh, it might not vnfitly be applied by the Cardinall to this purpoſe. For as <hi>Eleazar</hi> was a principall Scribe, ſo is he a principall Prieſt: As <hi>Eleazars</hi> example had a great force in it,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:22043:35"/>
to animate the yonger Scribes to keepe the Lawe, or in his colourable eating it, to haue taught them to diſſemble; So hath the Arch-prieſts, either to make the inferiour Prieſts to take the Oath, or to refuſe it: but the ground fayling, the building cannot ſtand. For what example is there in all the Scripture, in which diſobedience to the Oath of the King, or want of allegiance is allowed? If the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall would remember, that when the Church maketh a law (ſuppoſe to forbid fleſh on cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine daies) he that refuſeth to obey it, in cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the iuſt cenſure of the Church: If a man then ought to dye rather then to breake the leaſt of Gods Ceremoniall Laws, and to pine and ſtarue his body, rather then to violate the Church his poſitiue law: Will hee not giue leaue to a man to redeeme his ſoule from ſinne, and to keepe his body from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, by keeping the Kings politique lawe, and by giuing good example in his perſon, raiſe vp a good opinion in his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of like Allegiance in the inferiours of his order? This application, as I take it, would haue better fitted this example.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:22043:35"/>
But let mee remember the Cardinall of another <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 14. 24.</note> Oath inioyned by a King to his people, wherby he indangered his owne life, and hazarded the ſafety of the whole armie, when he made the people ſweare in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not to taſte of any meate vntill night: which oath hee exacted ſo ſtrictly, That his eldeſt ſonne and heire apparant <hi>Ionathan</hi> for breaking of it, by taking a litle honie, though he heard not when the King gaue it, had well nigh died for it. And ſhall an oath giuen vpon ſo vrgent an occaſion as this was, for the apparant ſafetie of the King and his poſterity, forbidding his people to drinke ſo deepely in the bitter cup of Antichriſtian fornications, but that they may keepe ſo much hony in their hearts, as may argue them ſtill eſpouſed to their Soueraigne in the maine knot of true allegiance; Shal this law, I ſay, by him bee condemned to hell for a ſtratageme of Sathan? I ſay no more, but Gods lot in that oath of <hi>Sauls,</hi> and his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict vpon this Oath of our Kings, ſeeme not to be caſt out of one lap.</p>
            <p>Now to his example of <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodoret lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Baſill,</hi> which is
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:22043:36"/>
(as hee ſaith) ſo fit for his purpoſe. Firſt, I muſt obſerue, that if the Cardinall would <note place="margin">An anſwere to the Card. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>S. Baſil.</hi>
               </note> leaue a common and ordinarie tricke of his in all his citations, which is, to take what makes for him, and leaue out what makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; and cite the authours ſenſe, as well as his ſentence; wee ſhould not be ſo much troubled with anſwering the Ancients which he alleadgeth. To inſtance it in this very place. If he had continued his allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one line further, hee ſhould haue found this place out of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> of more force to haue mooued <hi>Blackwell</hi> to take the Oath, then to haue diſſwaded him from it. For in the very next words it followeth, <hi>Imperatoris quidem amicitiam magni ſe pendere cum pietate; quâ remotâ, pernicioſum eſſe dicere.</hi> But that it may appeare, whether of vs haue greateſt right to this place, I will in few wordes ſhew the authors drift.</p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Valens</hi> being an Arrian, at the perſwaſion of his wife, when hee had depriued all the Churches of their Paſtors, came to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> where Saint <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodoret lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Baſill</hi> was then Biſhop; who, as the Story reporteth,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:22043:36"/>
was accounted the Light of the world. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came, he ſent his <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Modestus,</hi> as <hi>Nazian.</hi> vpon the death of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill,</hi> cals him in his Orat.</note> Deputie to worke it, that Saint <hi>Baſill</hi> ſhould hold fellowſhip with <hi>Eudoxius,</hi> (which <note n="b" place="margin">Looke cap. 12. <hi>ciuſdem libri.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eudoxius</hi> was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the principall of the Arrian Faction) or if he would not, that hee ſhould put him to baniſhment. Now when the Emperours Deputie came to <hi>Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> he ſent for <hi>Baſill,</hi> intreated him honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, ſpake pleaſingly vnto him, deſired he would giue way to the time, neither that he would hazard the good of ſo many Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>tenui exquiſitione Dogmatis,</hi> promiſed him the Emperours fauour, and himſelfe to be Mediator for his good. But Saint <hi>Baſill</hi> anſwered, <hi>Theſe intiſing ſpeeches were fit to be vſed to children, that vſe to gape after ſuch things: But for them that were throughly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in Gods word, they could neuer ſuffer any ſyllable thereof to be corrupted. Nay, if neede required, they would for the maintenance thereof, refuſe no kinde of death. Indeede the loue of the Emperour ought to be greatly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with Pietie; But Pietie taken away, it was pernicious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:22043:37"/>
This is the trueth of the Story. Now compare the caſe of <hi>Baſill</hi> with the Arch-prieſts. For otherwiſe ſo Orthodoxe a King ought not to be compared with ſo Arrian an Heretike. <hi>Baſill</hi> was ſolicited to become an Arrian: The Arch-prieſt not once touched for any Article of Faith. <hi>Baſill</hi> would haue obeyed the Emperour, but that the word of GOD forbade him: This man is willed to obey, becauſe the word of GOD comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him. <hi>Baſill</hi> highly eſteemed the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours fauour, if it might haue ſtood with pietie: The Arch-prieſt is exhorted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect it, though it ſtand with true godlineſſe in deede to embrace it. But that hee may <note place="margin">The Card. aſſimi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lating of the Archpr. caſe to <hi>S. Peters,</hi> and <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</note> lay load vpon the Arch-prieſt, it is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to exhort him to Courage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie by <hi>Eleazars</hi> and <hi>Baſils</hi> examples, but he muſt be vtterly caſt downe with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring his fall to <hi>S. Peters</hi> and <hi>Marcellinus:</hi> which two mens caſes were the moſt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, conſidering their perſons and places, that are to bee found, or read of either in all the Bookes of Diuine Scripture, or the volumes of Eccleſiaſticall Stories; the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:22043:37"/>
one denying the onely true God, the other our Lord and Sauiour IESVS CHRIST; the one ſacrificing to Idols with the profane Heathen, the other forſwearing his Lord and Maſter, with the hard-hearted Iewes. Vnles the Cardinall would driue the Arch-prieſt to ſome horror of conſcience, &amp; pit of deſpaire, I know not what he can meane by this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon. For ſure I am, all that are not intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with their cup, cannot but wonder to heare of an oath of Allegiance to a naturall Soueraigne, to be likened to an <hi>Apoſtats</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of God, &amp; forſwearing of his Sauiour.</p>
            <p>But to let paſſe the <hi>Diſdiapaſon</hi> of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (as his ill fauored coupling Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the head of their Church, with an Apoſtate Pope.) I maruaile he would remember this example of <note n="a" place="margin">Looke <hi>Platina in vita Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lini.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> ſince his brother Cardinall <hi>Baronius,</hi> and the late Edition of the Councels by <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 222. Looke <hi>Baronius Anno</hi> 302 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 96.</note> 
               <hi>Binnius</hi> ſeeme to call the credit of the whole Story into queſtion, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That it might plainely be refuted, and that it is probably to be ſhewed, that the ſtory is but obreptitious,</hi> but that hee would not ſwarue from the common receiued opinion.</p>
            <p>And
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:22043:38"/>
Subiects from their obedience to their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall King, nor bee ſo cruell to their owne <hi>Mancipia,</hi> as returning them with theſe wares, put either a State in iealouſie of them, or them in hazard of their owne liues. Now to our Apoſtle (ſince the Cardinall will haue him ſo called) I perſwade my ſelfe I ſhould doe a good ſeruice to the Church in this my labour, if I could but reape this one fruite of it, to moue the Cardinall to deale faithfully with the Fathers, and neuer to alleadge their opinions againſt their owne purpoſe. For, this letter of <hi>Gregorius</hi> was written to <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 42.</note> 
               <hi>Palermo</hi> in <hi>Sicily,</hi> to whom hee granted <hi>vſum pallij</hi> to be worne in ſuch times, and in ſuch order, as the Prieſts in the Ile of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and his Predeceſſours were wont to vſe: and withall giueth him a Caueat, that the reuerence to the Apoſtolique Sea be not diſturbed by the preſumption of any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For then the State of the members doeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſound, when the head of the faith is not broken by any iniury, and the authoritie of the Canons remaine ſafe and ſound.</p>
            <p>Now let vs examine the vvordes. The
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:22043:38"/>
Epiſtle was written to a Biſhop, eſpecially to graunt him the vſe of the Pall; a ceremonie and matter indifferent. As it appeareth, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> tooke it well at his hands, that hee would not preſume to take it vpon him without leaue from the Apoſtolike Sea, and giuing him that admonition which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the wordes alleadged out of him: which doctrine wee are ſo farre from impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that we altogether approue and allow of the ſame, That whatſoeuer Ceremonie for order is thought meete by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, and the Church, the ſame ought inuiolably to be kept: And where the Head and gouernours in matters of that nature are not obeyed, the members of that Church muſt needes runne to Helliſh confuſion. But that <hi>Gregory</hi> by that terme, <hi>Caput fidei,</hi> held himſelfe the head of our Faith, and the head of all Religion, cannot ſtand with the courſe of his doctrine and vvritings. For firſt, vvhen an <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohan. Conſtan. Greg. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 32.</note> other vvould haue had this ſtile to be called <hi>Vniuerſalis Epiſcopus,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Whoſoeuer would giue himſelfe that Title, was the Fore-runner of Antichriſt:</hi> Which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:22043:39"/>
vvas a Stile farre inferiour to that of <hi>Caput fidei.</hi> And vvhen it vvas of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to himſelfe, the vvords of Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> be theſe, refuſing that Title, <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 32. <hi>&amp;</hi> 36.</note> 
               <hi>That none of my Predeceſsors Biſhops of</hi> Rome, <hi>euer conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vſe this vngodly name of</hi> Vniuerſall Biſhop. <hi>None of the Biſhops of</hi> Rome <hi>euer tooke upon vs this name of Singularitie. Wee the Biſhops of</hi> Rome <hi>will not receiue this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour being offered vnto vs.</hi> And novv, I pray you, vvould he that refuſed to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Vniuerſall Biſhop, be ſtiled <hi>Caput fidei,</hi> vnleſſe it vvere in that ſenſe, as I haue expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Which ſenſe if you vvill not admit, giue me leaue to ſay that once of one, which himſelfe ſaith often of many of the Fathers, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de Rom. Pontif lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. &amp; lib.</hi> 2 <hi>de Chriſto cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Minùs cautè locutus eſt.</hi> To redeeme there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Apoſtle out of his hands, and to let him remaine ours, and not his in this caſe; It is very true that he ſaith, in that ſenſe hee ſpake it. When yee goe about to diſturbe, diminiſh, or take away the Authority or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of the Church, which reſteth on the head of the King within his Maieſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, ye cut off the head and chiefe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:22043:39"/>
thereof, and diſturbe the State and members of the whole Body. And for a Concluſion of this point, I pray him to thinke, that wee are ſo well perſwaded of the good mind of our Apoſtle Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> to vs, that wee deſire no other thing to be ſuggeſted to the Pope and his Cardinals, then our Apoſtle Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> deſired the Deputy of the Emperour <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Sabinian</hi> to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vnto the Emperour and the State in his time. His words be theſe: <hi>One thing there is of which I would deſire you would ſuggeſt it to your noble Lord and Maſter, That if I his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant would haue had my hand in ſtaying of the Lombards, at this day the Nation of the Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards had neither had Kings, nor Dukes, nor Earles, and had bene diuided aſunder in vtter confuſion: but becauſe I feare God, I dread to haue my hand in the blood of any man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus hauing anſwered to S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">An anſwere to the authoritie out of Leo.</note> I come to another Pope, his Apoſtle, S. <hi>Leo.</hi> And that hee may ſee I haue not in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Citations quareled him like a Sophiſter for contention ſake, but for finding out of the Truth; I do graunt, that the Authorities out
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:22043:40"/>
of <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leo primus in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ump. ſuae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Pontificat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mone</hi> 3. <hi>Leo epist.</hi> 89 <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piſc. V. en. Idem ibid. cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Leo</hi> are rightly alleadged all three, the words truely ſet downe, together with his true intent and purpoſe. But withall, let me tell him, and I appeale vnto his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence whether I ſpeake not truely, that what <hi>Tully</hi> ſayd to <note n="c" place="margin">Cicero in Hort.</note> 
               <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> when he did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderatly praiſe Eloquence, that he would haue lift her vp to heauen, that himſelfe might haue gone vp with her; So his Saint <hi>Leo</hi> lift vp Saint <hi>Peter</hi> with praiſes to the Skie, that he being his <note n="d" place="margin">For ſo he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth himſelfe <hi>in ſermo.</hi> 1. <hi>in die <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſsum.</hi>
               </note> heire, might haue gone vp with him. For his Saint <hi>Leo</hi> was a great Orator, who by the power of his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence redeemed <hi>Rome</hi> from fire, when both <note n="e" place="margin">Exbreniario Romano.</note> 
               <hi>Attilas</hi> and <hi>Genſericus</hi> would haue burnt it.</p>
            <p>Some fruits of this Rhetorick he beſtowed vpon Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Lord</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 89.</note> 
               <hi>did take Peter into the fellowſhip of the indiuiſible vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> which words being coupled to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence alleadged by the Cardinall <hi>(That hee hath no part in the diuine Myſtery that dare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the ſolidity of Peter)</hi> ſhould haue giuen him, I thinke, ſuch a Sare, as he ſhould neuer haue dared to haue taken any aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:22043:40"/>
by the words immediatly preceding, for the benefit of the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the head thereof, ſince thoſe which immediatly follow, are ſo much derogatory to the diuine Maieſtie. And againe, <hi>My</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 52.</note> 
               <hi>writings bee ſtrengthned by the merit, and Authority of my Lord moſt bleſſed Saint Peter. We</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 89.</note> 
               <hi>beſeech you to keepe the things decreed by vs thorough the inſpiration of God, and the Apoſtle moſt bleſſed Saint Peter. If</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>In ſer.</hi> 2. <hi>in die an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er. aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um. ſuae.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>any thing be well done, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed of vs; If any thing be obtained of Gods mercy by dayly prayers, it is to be aſcribed to Saint Peters works, and merits, whoſe power doth liue, and Authority excell in his owne Sea. He</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ser.</hi> 3. <hi>in die ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. aſſump ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>was ſo plentifully watered of the fountaine of all Graces, that whereas hee receiued many things alone, yet nothing paſſeth ouer to any man but by him.</hi> And in a word, he was ſo deſirous to extoll Saint <hi>Peter, That a meſſage from him was an</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Embaſſage from S. Peter: Any thing done in his preſence, was in Saint Peters</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</hi> Neither did he vſe all this Rhetorick without purpoſe: for at that time the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> contended with him for Primacy. And in the Councell of <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Calc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Act.</hi> 16. <hi>c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 28</note> 
               <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:22043:41"/>
the Biſhops ſixe hundred and more gaue equall Authority to the Patriark of that Sea, and would not admit any priuiledge to the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> aboue him, but went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. And yet hee that gaue ſo much to <hi>Peter,</hi> tooke nothing from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but gaue him both his Titles and due, giuing the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of calling a Councell to the Emperour, as it may appeare by theſe one or two places following of many. <hi>If it may pleaſe your</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epi.</hi> 9. <hi>Theodo ſio.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, to vouchſafe at our Supplication to condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend, that you will command a Councell to be holden within Italy.</hi> And writing vnto the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Conſtantinople: <hi>Becauſe the moſt Clement</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 16. <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiano.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Emperour, carefull of the peace of the Church, will haue a Councell to be holden; Albeit it euidently appeare, the matter to be handled doth in no caſe ſtand in neede of a generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. Albeit</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 17. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſio.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>my occaſions will not permit me to be preſent vpon the day of the Councell, which your Godlineſſe hath appointed.</hi> So as by this it may well appeare, that he that gaue ſo much to <hi>Peter,</hi> gaue alſo to <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue. But yet he playeth not faire play in this, that euen in all theſe his wrong ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:22043:41"/>
Arguments, and Examples, he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth no other witneſſes, but the parties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, bringing euer the Popes Sentences for approbation of their owne Authority.</p>
            <p>Now indeede for one word of his in the middeſt of his Examples, I cannot but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend him, that is, that Martyrs ought to indure all ſorts of tortures, and death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſuffer one ſyllable to be corrupted of the Law of God. Which leſſon, if he and all the reſt of his owne profeſsion would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie to themſelues, then would not the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament be adminiſtred <hi>ſub vnâ ſpecie,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to Chriſts Inſtitution, the practiſe of the Apoſtles, and of the whole Primatiue Church for many hundred yeres: then would not the priuate Maſſes bee in place of the Lords Supper: then would not the words of the <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. de ſacra. Euchariſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> Canon of the Maſſe be oppoſed to the wordes of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> as our Aduerſary himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, and cannot reconcile them: nor then would not ſo many hundreths other Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men be ſet vp in their Church, not only as equall, but euen preferred to the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:22043:42"/>
word of God. But ſure in this point I feare I haue miſtaken him: for I thinke he doth not meane by his <hi>Diuina dogmata,</hi> the word of the God of heauen, but onely the Canons and Lawes of his <hi>Dominus Deus Papa:</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe all his Primacy of the Apoſtolike Sea would not bee ſo much ſticken vpon, hauing ſo ſlender ground in the word of God.</p>
            <p>And for the great feare he hath, that the ſuddainty of the Apprehenſion, the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Perſecution, the weakeneſſe of his Age, and other ſuch infirmities might haue bene the cauſe of the Arch-prieſts fal; in this, I haue already ſufficiently anſwered him, hauing declared, as the trueth is, and as the ſaid <hi>Blackwell</hi> himſelfe will yet teſtifie, That hee tooke this Oath freely of himſelfe without any inducement thereunto, either <hi>Precibus</hi> or <hi>Minis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But amongſt all his citations, he muſt not <note place="margin">Some of Sanders his worthy ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</note> forget holy <hi>Sanderus,</hi> and his <hi>Viſibilis Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchia,</hi> whoſe perſon and actions I did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a little touch. And ſurely, who will with vnpartiall eyes reade his Bookes, they
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:22043:42"/>
may well thinke, that he hath deſerued well of his Engliſh Roman-Church: But they can neuer thinke, but that he deſerued very ill of his Engliſh Soueraigne and State. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe his owne bookes: whereout I haue made choice to ſet downe heere theſe fewe Sentences following, as flowers pickt out of ſo worthy a Garland. <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sand. de viſib. monar. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> ELIZABETH <hi>Queene of</hi> England <hi>doeth exerciſe the Prieſtly acte of teaching and preaching the Goſpell in</hi> England, <hi>with no leſſe authority then</hi> CHRIST <hi>himſelfe, or</hi> MOSES <hi>euer did. The Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of a</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sand de cla. Dauid. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>woman in Church matters, is from no other, then from the Deuill.</hi> And of all Kings in generall, thus hee ſpeaketh, <hi>The</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sand. de viſib. Monar. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>King that will not inthrall himſelfe to the Popes authority, he ought not to be tollerated, but his Subiects ought to giue all diligence, that another may be choſen in his place aſſoone as may be. A King that is an</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Heretike, ought to be remoued from the Kingdome that he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth amongſt Chriſtians, and the Biſhops ought to endeuour to ſet vp another, aſſoone as poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly they can. We doe conſtantly</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>affirme, that all Chriſtian Kings are ſo farre vnder Biſhops</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:22043:43"/>
               <hi>and Prieſts in all matters appertaining to Faith and Religion, that if they ſhall continue in a fault againſt Chriſtian Religion after one or two admonitions, obſtinately, for that cauſe they may, and ought to bee depoſed by the Biſhops from all the Authority they hold amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Biſhops are ſet ouer Imperiall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, if thoſe Kingdomes do ſubmit themſelues to the Faith of</hi> CHRIST. <hi>We doe conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sand. de clau. Dauid. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>affirme, That all Secular power, whether Regall, or any other, is of Men. The</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oynting which is powred vpon the head of the King by the Prieſt, doeth declare that he is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the Prieſt. It is altogether againſt the will of</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sand. de clau Dauid lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> CHRIST, <hi>that Chriſtian Kings ſhould haue Supremacy in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas for the Crowne, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of all his examples, he reckoneth his <note place="margin">The Card. paire of Martyrs weighed.</note> two Engliſh Martyrs, <hi>Moore</hi> and <hi>Roffenſis,</hi> who died for that one moſt weightie head of Doctrine, as he alleadgeth, refuſing the Oath of Supremacie; I muſt tell him, that he hath not bene well informed in ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall points, which doe very neerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne his two ſaid Martyrs. For it is cleare,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:22043:43"/>
and apparantly to be proued by diuers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, That they were both of them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Tower about a yeere before either of them was called in queſtion vpon their liues for the Popes Supremacy; And that partly for their backwardneſſe in the point of the eſtabliſhment of the Kings Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion, whereunto the whole Realme had ſubſcribed, and partly for that one of them, to wit, <hi>Fiſher,</hi> had had his hand in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the holy <note n="a" place="margin">Called <hi>Anna Burton,</hi> See the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> maid of <hi>Kent,</hi> he being for his concealement of that falſe Prophets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, found guilty of Miſpriſion of Treaſon. And as theſe were the principall cauſes of their Impriſonment, (the King reſting ſecure of his Supremacy as the Realme ſtood then affected, but eſpecially troubled for ſetling the Crowne vpon the Iſſue of his ſecond Marriage) So was it eaſily to be conceiued, that being thereupon diſcontented, their humors were thereby made apt to drawe them by degrees to further oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King and his Authority, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it fell out. For in the time of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in priſon, the Kings lawfull Authoritie
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:22043:44"/>
in caſes Eccleſiaſticall being publiſhed and promulged, as well by a generall Decree of the Clergie in their Synode, as by an Acte of Parliament made thereupon; they beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued themſelues ſo peeuiſhly therein; as the old coales of the Kings anger being thereby raked vp of new, they were againe brought in queſtion, as well for this one moſt weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie head of Doctrine of the Pope his Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, as for the matter of the Kings marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Succeſsion, as by the confeſsion of one of themſelues, euen <hi>Thomas Moore,</hi> is euident. For being condemned, hee vſed theſe words at the Barre before the Lords, <hi>Non ignoro cur me morti adiudicaueritis, vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet ob id, quod nunquam voluerim aſſentire in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. aliquot Martyrum noſtri ſeculi, Anno</hi> 1550.</note> 
               <hi>negotio Matrimonij Regis.</hi> That is, <hi>I am not ignorant why you haue adiudged me to death: to wit, for that I would neuer conſent in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of the new marriage of the King.</hi> By which his owne confeſsion it is plaine, that this great Martyr himſelfe tooke the cauſe of his owne death, to be onely for his being refractary to the King in this ſaid matter of Marriage and Succeſsion; which is but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:22043:44"/>
fleſhly cauſe of Martyrdom, as I conceiue.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Roffenſis</hi> his fellow Martyr, (who could haue bene content to haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the oath of the Kings Supremacy, with a certaine modification, which <hi>Moore</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) as his impriſonment was neither only, nor principally for the cauſe of Supremacy; ſo dyed he but a halting and a ſingular Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, or witnes for that moſt waightie head of doctrine, the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that time in one current and ſtreame as it were againſt him in that Argument, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of them being of farre greater reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for learning and ſound iudgement then euer he was. So as in this point we may well arme our ſelues with the Cardinals owne reaſon, where he giueth amongſt other notes of the true Church, <hi>Vniuerſality</hi> for one, we hauing the generall and Catholike conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> on our ſide in this caſe, as appeareth by their booke ſet out by the whole Conuocation of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> called, <hi>The Institution of a Chriſtian man;</hi> the ſame matter being likewiſe very learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled by diuers particular learned men
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:22043:45"/>
of our Church, as by <hi>Steuen Gardiner</hi> in his booke <hi>De vera Obedientia,</hi> with a Preface of Biſhop <hi>Boners</hi> adioyned to it, <hi>De ſummo &amp; abſoluto Regis imperio,</hi> publiſhed by Maſter <hi>Bekinſaw, De vera differentia Regiae Potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; Eccleſiae,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Tonstals</hi> Sermon, Biſhop <hi>Longlands</hi> Sermon, the letter of <hi>Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall</hi> to Cardinall <hi>Poole,</hi> and diuers other both in Engliſh and Latine. And if the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of <hi>Fiſhers</hi> diſcontentment had not bin fed with his daily ambitious expectation of the Cardinals hat, which came ſo neere as <hi>Calis</hi> before he loſt his head to fill it with, I haue great reaſon to doubt, if hee would haue conſtantly perſeuered in induring his Martyrdome for that one moſt waightie head of doctrine.</p>
            <p>And ſurely theſe two Captaines and ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders to Martyrdome were but ill followed by the reſt of their countrymen: for I can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reade of any after them, being of any great account, and that not many, that euer ſealed that waightie head of doctrine with their blood in <hi>England.</hi> So as the true cauſes of their firſt falling in trouble (whereof I haue
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:22043:45"/>
already made mention) being rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered vpon the one part; and vpon the other the ſcant number of witneſſes, that with their blood ſealed; (a point ſo greatly accounted of by our Cardinall) there can but ſmall glory redound thereby to our Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, theſe only two, <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for witneſſes againſt our Antichriſtian doctrine.</p>
            <p>And I am ſure the Supremacy of Kings <note place="margin">The ſupremacie of Kings ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently warranted by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> may and will euer be better maintained by the word of God (which muſt euer be the true rule to diſcerne all waightie heads of doctrine by) to be the true and proper of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſtian Kings in their owne Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, then he will be euer able to maintaine his annihilating Kings, and their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, together with his baſe and vnreuerend ſpeeches of them, wherewith both his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer great Volumes, and his late Bookes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Venice</hi> are filled. In the old Teſtament, Kings were directly <note n="a" place="margin">2. Chron. 19. 4.</note> Gouernours ouer the Church within their Dominions, <note n="b" place="margin">2. Sam. 5. 6.</note> purged their corruptions, reformed their abuſes, brought the <note n="c" place="margin">1. Chron. 13. 12.</note> Arke to her reſting place: the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:22043:46"/>
King <note n="e" place="margin">2. Sam. 6. 16</note> dauncing before it, <note n="f" place="margin">1. Chro. 28. 6.</note> built the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <note n="g" place="margin">2. Chron. 6.</note> dedicated the ſame, aſsiſting in their owne perſons to the ſanctification thereof, <note n="h" place="margin">2. King. 22 1</note> made the booke of the Lawe new-found, to be read to the people; <note n="i" place="margin">Nehe. 9. 38 Dauid. Salomon. 2. Kings 8. 4.</note> renued the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betweene God, and his people; bruſed the braſen Serpent in peeces, which was ſet vp by the expreſſe commandement of God, and was a figure of Chriſt; deſtroyed <note n="k" place="margin">1. Kings 15. 12. 2 kings 13. 4.</note> all Idols, and falſe gods; made <note n="l" place="margin">2. Chron. 7. 8.</note> a publike refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, by a Commiſsion of Prieſts and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men mixed for that purpoſe; depoſed <note n="m" place="margin">1. Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 27.</note> the High Prieſt, and ſet vp another in his place: and generally, ordered euery thing belonging to the Church-gouernment, their Titles and Prerogatiues giuen them by God, agreeing to theſe their actions. They are called <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">2. Sam. 7 4</note> 
               <hi>Sonnes of the Moſt High,</hi> nay <hi>Gods</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 82. 6 &amp; Exod. 23. 8</note> 
               <hi>themſelues; The</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">1. Chron. 14. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Lords anoynted; Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">2. Sam. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. Chron. 6. 15</note> 
               <hi>in Gods Throne; His</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>ſeruants: The Angels</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Sam. 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <hi>of God: According to his</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">1. Sam. 13. 4</note> 
               <hi>hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; The light</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">2. Sam. 21 7</note> 
               <hi>of Iſrael; The</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 49. 23</note> 
               <hi>nurſing fathers of the Church,</hi> with innumerable ſuch ſtiles of honour, wherewith the old Teſtament is filled, whereof our Aduerſary can pretend
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:22043:46"/>
no ignorance. And as to the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Euery ſoule</hi> is commanded <hi>to be ſubiect vnto them, euen for</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 13 5</note> 
               <hi>conſcience ſake:</hi> All men <note n="z" place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 2</note> muſt be prayed for; <hi>but eſpecially Kings, and thoſe that are in Authority; that vnder them we may leade a godly, peaceable, and an honeſt life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13. 4</note> 
               <hi>Magistrate is the minister of God to doe vengeance on him that doth euill, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him that doth well. Ye muſt obey all higher Powers, but</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 13</note> 
               <hi>eſpecially Princes, and thoſe that are Supereminent. Giue euery man his due, feare</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 13. 7</note> 
               <hi>to whome feare belongeth, and loue to whome loue belongeth. Giue</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 22 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>vnto Caeſar what is Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars, and to God what is Gods.</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 18. 36</note> 
               <hi>Regnum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um non eſt huius mundi.</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 12. 14</note> 
               <hi>Quis me constituit Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicem ſuper vos?</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Luke 22. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Reges gentium dominantur eorum; vos autem non ſic.</hi> If theſe Sentences, Titles, and Prerogatiues, and innumerable other in the old and new Teſtament, do not warrant Chriſtian Kings within their owne Dominions, to gouerne their Church, as well as the reſt of their people, in being <hi>Custodes vtriuſque tabulae,</hi> not by making new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith, which is the Popes office, as I
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:22043:47"/>
ſaid before, but by commanding obedience to be giuen to the word of God, by refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Religion according to his preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed will, by aſsiſting the Spirituall power with the Temporall Sword, by reforming of corruptions, by procuring due obedience to the Church, by iudging, and cutting off all friuolous Queſtions and Schiſmes, as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> did; And finally, by making <hi>Decorum</hi> to be obſerued in euery thing, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing orders to be obſerued in all indifferent things for that purpoſe, which is the only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of our Oath of Supremacy: If this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a King, I ſay, doe not agree with the power giuen him by Gods word, let any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different man voyd of paſsion iudge. But how theſe honorable Offices, Stiles, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues giuen by God to Kings in the old and new Teſtament, as I haue now cited, can agree with the braue Stiles and Titles that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> giueth them, I can hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. <note n="1" place="margin">
                  <hi>De laicis ca.</hi> 7.</note> That <hi>Kings are rather ſlaues then Lords.</hi> 
               <note n="2" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Pont. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> That <hi>they are not only Subiects to Popes, to Biſhops, to Prieſts, but euen to Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</hi> 
               <note n="3" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> That <hi>an Emperor muſt content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:22043:47"/>
               <hi>to drinke, not onely after a Biſhop, but after a Biſhops Chaplen.</hi> 
               <note n="4" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem, &amp; de cler. cap</hi> 26.</note> That <hi>Kings haue not their Authoritie, nor Office from God, nor his Lawe, but onely from the Lawe of Nations.</hi> 
               <note n="5" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Pont. lib.</hi> 3 <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> That <hi>Popes haue degraded many Emperors, but neuer Emperour degraded a Pope; nay, euen Biſhops, that are but the Popes vaſſals, may depoſe Kings, and abrogate their Lawes.</hi> 
               <note n="6" place="margin">
                  <hi>De laicis cap.</hi> 18.</note> That <hi>Church-men are as farre aboue Kings, as the Soule aboue the Body.</hi> 
               <note n="7" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Pont. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap</hi> 8.</note> That <hi>Kings may bee depoſed by their people for diuerſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</hi> 
               <note n="8" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Pout. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>But Popes cannot be depoſed: for no fleſh hath power to iudge of them.</hi> 
               <note n="9" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Pont. lib.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> That <hi>obedience due to the Pope, is for Conſcience ſake.</hi> 
               <note n="10" place="margin">
                  <hi>De clericis cap.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>But the obedience due to Kings, is onely for certaine reſpects of Order &amp; Policie.</hi> 
               <note n="11" place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idem.</note> That <hi>theſe very Church men that are borne and inhabite in Soueraigne Princes Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, are notwithſtanding not their Subiects, and cannot be iudged by them, although they may iudge them;</hi> 
               <note n="12" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> And, that <hi>the obedience that Church men giue to Princes, euen in the meaneſt, and meere Temporall things, is not by way of neceſſary ſubiection, but onely out of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion for obſeruation of good Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:22043:48"/>
Theſe contrarieties betweene the Booke of God, and <hi>Bellarmines</hi> bookes, haue I here ſet in oppoſition to other, <hi>Vt ex contrarijs iuxta ſe poſitis, veritas magis eluceſcere poſsit.</hi> And thus farre I dare boldly affirme, That whoſoeuer will indifferently weigh theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcileable Contradictions here ſet down, will eaſily confeſſe, that GOD is no more contrary to Belial, Light to Darkeneſſe, and Heauen to Hell, then <hi>Bellarmines</hi> eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Kings is to Gods.</p>
            <p>Now as to the concluſion of his Letter, which is onely filled with ſtrong and pithy Exhortations, to perſwade and confirme <hi>Blackwell</hi> to the patient and conſtant indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Martyrdome, I haue nothing to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, ſaue by way of regrate; That ſo many good ſentences drawen out of the Scripture, ſo well and ſo handſomely packed vp toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhould be ſo ill and vntruely applied. But an euill Cauſe is neuer the better for ſo good a Cloake; And an ill matter neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by good wordes: And therefore I may iuſtly turne ouer that craft of the Deuill vpon himſelfe, in vſing ſo Holy-like an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:22043:48"/>
to ſo euill a purpoſe. Onely I could haue wiſhed him, that he had a litle better obſerued his <hi>Decorum</hi> herein, in not letting ſlippe two or three prophane wordes amongſt ſo many godly mortified Scripture ſentences. For in all the Scripture, eſpecially in the New Teſtament, I neuer read of <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex Maximus.</hi> And the Pope muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in that ſtile to ſucceede to <hi>Numa Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius,</hi> and not to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> who neuer heard nor dreamed of ſuch an office.</p>
            <p>And for his <hi>Caput fidei,</hi> which I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred before, the Apoſtles, I am ſure, neuer gaue that ſtile to any but to CHRIST. So as theſe ſtiles, whereof ſome were neuer found in Scripture, and ſome were neuer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied but to CHRIST in that ſenſe, as hee applieth it, had bene better to haue bene left out of ſo holy and mortified a Letter.</p>
            <p>To conclude then this preſent Diſcourſe, I heartily wiſh all indifferent readers of the <hi>Breues</hi> and Letter, not to iudge by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe of the wordes, but by the weight of the matter; Not looking to that which is ſtrongly alledged, but iudiciouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:22043:49"/>
what is iuſtly proued; And for all our Soueraignes good Subiects, that their hearts may remaine eſtabliſhed in the Trueth; That theſe forraine inticements may not ſeduce them from their naturall duety; And that all, aſwell Strangers as Naturall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, to whoſe eyes this Diſcourſe ſhall come, may wiſely and vnpartially iudge of the Veritie, as it is nakedly here ſet downe, for clearing theſe miſtes and cloudes of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, which were iniuſtly heaped vpon our Soueraigne: For which ende onely I heartily pray the courteous Reader to be perſwaded, that this diſcourſe was publiſhed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22043:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
